<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The creatures goodness, as they came out of God's hands, and the good mans mercy to the brute creatures, which God hath put under his feet in two sermons : the first preached before the University of Oxford : the second at the lecture at Brackley / by Thomas Hodges ...</title>
            <author>Hodges, Thomas, d. 1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44070</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2319</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17986</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11742331</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11742331</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48506</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44070)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48506)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 534:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The creatures goodness, as they came out of God's hands, and the good mans mercy to the brute creatures, which God hath put under his feet in two sermons : the first preached before the University of Oxford : the second at the lecture at Brackley / by Thomas Hodges ...</title>
                  <author>Hodges, Thomas, d. 1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
               <term>Animal welfare.</term>
               <term>Mercy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48506:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48506:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Creatures Goodneſs, As they came out of God's Hands, AND THE GOOD MANS MERCY TO THE BRUTE CREATURES, Which God hath put under his Feet.</p>
            <p>IN TWO SERMONS, The firſt Preached before the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> The ſecond at the Lecture at <hi>Brackley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Hodges,</hi> B. D. late Rector of <hi>Souldern</hi> in <hi>OXFORDSHIRE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the Bible and three Crowns in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:48506:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48506:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the much Honoured <hi>RICHARD WINWOOD,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Here humbly preſent to you, and under your Name and Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage publiſh to the World two Sermons, the one concerning the primitive Goodneſs of the Creatures as they firſt came out of God's hand; the other, of the righteous Man's goodneſs, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and mercy to the Creatures, which God hath put into his hand, or under his feet. If any queſtion me for preaching on the firſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, ſaying, wherefore is this loſs? My anſwer is, that God himſelf,<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.</note> who is infinitely wiſe, did preach on the Creatures goodneſs and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency unto <hi>Job,</hi> and thereby brought him on his knees,<note place="margin">See Job. Ch. 38, 39, 40, 41.</note> even to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor himſelf in duſt and aſhes. That <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wiſeſt of Men ſince <hi>Adam,</hi> ſhewed his Wiſdom not in Metaphyſical Speculations or No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, not in Logical Sophiſms or Terms of Art, not in Philological Criticiſms: But in that he ſpake of Trees, <hi>from the Cedar-tree that is in</hi> Libanon <hi>unto the Hyſſop that ſpringeth out of the Wall; he ſpake alſo of Beaſts, and of Fowls,<note place="margin">1 Kings. 4.33. &amp;c.</note> and of creeping Things, and of Fiſhes.</hi> And I have heard of Mr. <hi>Wheatly</hi> of <hi>Banbury,</hi> an eloquent and a famous Preacher, that he made a whole Sermon in commendation of a Horſe. And truly where God gives a Text, and preaches on it himſelf, his Ministers have a ſufficient war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to make a Sermon. As for my choice of the ſubject of the ſecond Sermon and my Diſcourſe thereon; my apology is, if it need one, that it hath often grieved my Soul, to ſee how the poor bruit Beaſts have been uſed, or abuſed rather, by their inhumane, mercileſs, abſurd, &amp; unreaſonable cruel Maſters, <hi>who having no underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came worſe than the Beaſt that periſheth.</hi> And I would, if it was poſſible, put a ſtop to the rage of brutiſh Men, and however hear teſtimony to the truth, namely, that 'tis a good Character of a good Man to be merciful to his Beaſt.</p>
            <p>As for this Addreſs to you; I may ſay that of all Men living of quality that I have known, you are moſt free from this fault. You are
<pb facs="tcp:48506:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
like the good Man in the Text, you do regard the life of your Beaſt. And I wiſh all your Servants may be like their Maſter, or like <hi>Elea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zir,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Steward, that had ſuch a care of his Masters Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels. Further, <hi>SIR,</hi> give me leave to tell you that I have read a Treatiſe of <hi>Monſieur de la Chambre,</hi> to prove that Beaſts have reaſon;<note place="margin">B. M.</note> and that one of the Ancients ſaith, that <hi>Canis</hi> is <hi>Logicus, Ethicus, Theologus.</hi> Now, if ſo it be, that Dogs make Syllogiſms, and that they do <hi>diſcurrere</hi> as well as <hi>currere,</hi> diſcourſe as well as courſe, I preſume you may know as well as moſt Gentleman in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Honoured <hi>SIR,</hi> although I never did preach to thoſe ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational Animals (as the Book of Conformities tells us S. <hi>Francis</hi> did to the Wolf, and the Birds,) to teach them their duty to God or Man; nor do I pretend to preach in theſe Sermons to ſtir up Men's Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from what is reported of the great Reverence which S. <hi>Anthony</hi>'s Mule,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V. D. S.</hi> 2. D. p. 502.</note> S. <hi>Francis</hi> his Sheep, and the Cook of <hi>Lisbon</hi>'s Dog ſhew'd to the Sacrament; yet I may and muſt profeſs to learn Gratitude to my Benefactours, and particularly to your Worthy ſelf from <hi>Patroclus</hi> his Lyon, who fawned on him when thrown to him in the Theatre at <hi>Rome</hi> to be devoured by him,<note place="margin">A. G. l. 5. c. 14.</note> and all this for a good turn the Man had formerly done him in <hi>Africa</hi> by pulling ſomething out of the Lyons foot that hurt him. <hi>SIR,</hi> I ſhall not hold you long in the porch by prefixing a large Epiſtle to ſo ſmall a Piece; I ſhall only add one hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and hearty Requeſt unto all Gentlemen who delight in Hunting, who ſhall read theſe Sermons, if any ſuch ſhall happen to caſt their eyes in them: That they would often think of <hi>Amedeus,</hi> Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who was choſen Pope, but too good to hold it, who ſhewing a Company of poor People nouriſhed by him, ſaid theſe were the Hounds wherewithal he did hunt after the Kingdom of Heaven. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever never to take the Childrens bread to caſt it to the Dogs; I mean, to provide always that the Poor may not fare the worſe, becauſe their Hounds fare ſo well. And ſo I conclude with my humble and hearty Requeſt to the Almighty GOD for you, that he would be pleaſed long to continue you a Lover, Practiſer, and Countenancer of the true Proteſtant Religion, a loyal Subject to his Majeſty, a worthy Patriot, a Son of Peace, and like that great and good Man your Father (when he was Ambaſſadour in <hi>Holland</hi> remonſtrated againſt <hi>Vorſtius</hi>) a Lover of the Truth, and a Lover of good Men. So wiſhing you, and your virtuous and religious Conſort, all happineſs, I reſt as in duty bound,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your obliged humble Servant <hi>T. H.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May the 12th. 1675.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48506:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Gen. I. Part of the 31. Verſe.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And God ſaw every thing that he had made, and behold it was very good.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE Holy Scriptures, even from the beginning of them, ſpeak of God <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men; And becauſe 'tis the ordinary pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the beſt Artificers, often to take a view of the works under their hands, to compare them with the Idea which they have in their minds, or with the Model or Pattern which they have before their eyes, to the end to ſee how well they agree thereunto; Therefore alſo doth the Text repreſent to us Almighty God, the great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitect, Builder, or Maker of Heaven and Earth, and the Sea and all things therein, having in ſix days finiſhed this glorious Fabrick, now in the cloſe of the ſixth day taking a general ſurvey or review of all his works, (as it were) to ſee whether all things were made, according to the Idea or plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form of things which he had in his own mind from all eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; to ſee (as it were) whether there was any neceſſary Creature wanting, any thing made ſuperfluous or redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, how the ſeveral particulars did correſpond and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire to adorn the Univerſe, whether any <hi>Momus</hi> or <hi>Ariſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> could ever after come forth and juſtly criticiſe upon any of his works, upon any tittle or jota in all the great Book of the Creatures from the beginning to the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>And God ſaw every thing that he had made.</hi> And when God had viewed and reviewed, ſuperviſed and reviſed his whole work, and every particular of it; he paſſed judgment, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judgment, and that with a Sentence of approbation and commendation upon every particular thing which he had made. <hi>And behold</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>it was very good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48506:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>God's <hi>ſurvey</hi> of all his Creatures; and his judgment of them upon his ſurvey and review of them; theſe two divide the Text. From the words we ſhall deduce theſe two Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That God, who is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, he doth look upon again &amp; again, and conſider his works.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That it is a true and righteous Sentence or Judgment, namely this which he paſſed upon his Creatures at firſt, as they then were, as they came out of his hands: <hi>Behold they were very good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The former I ſhall very briefly diſpatch, the latter I ſhall inſiſt upon.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Of the firſt. It cannot be that ever any thing ſhould be hid from Gods all-ſeeing Eye, which is a thouſand times brighter than the Sun; Which if it look on the Sun, the eye of the World, that ſhineth not; yea God who is All-eye, <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus oculus,</hi> ſees more than the eye of Faith doth, and yet that ſees things that are inviſible; and therefore nothing which was regiſtred in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Natural Hiſtory of the Creation, could poſſibly lye undiſcovered unto him. No not the Angels of Heaven above, which becauſe not to be ſeen with corporal eyes, much leſs Minerals hid in the bowels of the Earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, which becauſe not actually ſeen without much dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and delving, or becauſe not ſo ſoon perfected by the heat of the Sun, are therefore omitted altogether in the preceding Narration; I ſay there was never any thing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> either in Heaven above, in the Earth beneath, or in the Waters either above or under the Earth, which was not alway viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and actually ſeen and beheld by him. And yet, if you look over this Chapter, you will find that 'tis ſaid that God had ſeen his works four times before now. He ſaw the work of every day in the end thereof, and pronounced it good, except the ſecond day; which ſome think was becauſe the Angels were created that day, and that day fell multitudes of them; Others becauſe that day was a work of diviſion; for then God made the Firmament, and divided the Waters which were under the Firmament, from the Waters which were above the Firmament, <hi>verſe</hi> 7. Or laſtly and moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48506:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
becauſe the work which was begun that day was not ſo fully perfected until the third day, when God gathered the Waters under the Heaven into one place, and call'd it Seas, when 'tis ſaid, that <hi>God ſaw that it was good.</hi> Verſ. 10. I ſay, God had ſeen his works four times before this ſixth day; and never looked on any thing that he had made, but he ſaw it was good; and yet this ſatisfies not, but he ſees and ſurveys them again a fifth time, namely now on the ſixth day, <hi>God ſaw every thing that he had made.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any wonder at this, and ſay in their heart, what doth this mean? if it was ſo, why was it thus? I anſwer, that it was not done for that it was poſſible for God to have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen himſelf in any of his works, and to have omitted either any part or parcel of work which he had deſigned to do, or any punctilio of workmanſhip requiſite; It was not becauſe that any thing either actually did, or poſſibly could miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in his hands, or be marred by him in the making of it: It was not becauſe there was any want of harmony, or due proportion of the parts one to another, or becauſe all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they could poſſibly render the Univerſe ugly or mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous. It was not for any one, nor for all theſe cauſes put together, that God is ſaid thus often to ſee his works: But it may be for ſome ſuch ends as theſe;</p>
               <p n="1">1. To teach us ſeriouſly to contemplate, and wiſely to conſider the operation of his hands, to ſtudy the Book of Nature well, that large Volume of two Tomes, Heaven and Earth; and therein to ſee the inviſible things of God, even his eternal Power and Godhead, which being of themſelves not ſeen, yet are manifeſt by the things that do appear. In the Sun, Moon, and Stars you may ſee <hi>digitum Dei;</hi> In the inferior or ſublunary Creatures <hi>veſtigia Dei,</hi> Gods footſteps, for <hi>quaelibet Herba &amp; quaelibet Beſtiola Deum refert.</hi> In Man you may ſee <hi>Dei Speculum &amp; Imaginem,</hi> the Glaſs, Image, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of God. In the Univerſe, as in a fair Book and very legible Characters, you may read, yea you may run and read, the Name and Nature of God; and by reading and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this Book only, you may prove good Scholars in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity. God would have no Atheiſt in the Univerſity of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48506:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
World: But if any ſuch there be, who ſhut their eyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the light of the knowledge of God in the face of the whole Creation, let them know that God's eye is ever upon them, and that for evil, for this horrid ingratitude, in that that they would ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him that made them, not allow him a being who give them, and all things or Creatures elſe, theirs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To teach us to view and review our own works. If God, who could not err, ſurveyed every days work (one excepted) in the end of the day, and the whole weeks work in the end of the ſixth day: Let us go and do likewiſe; Let's conſider our ways daily, and again let's conſider our ways weekly; Let there be no man amongſt us, but who reviews his works, ſaying, <hi>What have I done?</hi> This was the way where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>David</hi> (if we judge him the pen-man of the 119. Pſalm) was converted, or reſtored after his fall, he <hi>thought on his ways,</hi> look'd them over and over again, and <hi>turn'd his feet unto God's Teſtimonies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. To ſecure to himſelf his own honour and glory, and to render the Creatures inexcuſable, in caſe of any future miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage. Now if any thing fall, and be marr'd, the fault cannot juſtly and reaſonally be imputed unto God; for he was exceeding careful to make, and overlook, and examine his works, and to make and leave all well, good, and very good. If therefore there happen hereafter to be any errour, any crack, flaw, ſpot or blur, any fault in any of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, it muſt be acknowledged to be by ſome abuſe, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, miſcarriage, or fall out of our hands: for, before they came out of God's hands, he looked them over and over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and found and left them all right and good, and very or vehemently good.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To prevent our carping, quarrelling and finding fault with God's works, <hi>Ne aliter de ſuis operibus ſentire vel loqui quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam audeat.</hi> Calvin. That we ſay not, no not in our hearts, <hi>Cui bono?</hi> Or, <hi>Quorſum perditio haec?</hi> Concerning any of the Creatures, that none may ſay, What is this? Wherefore is that? For all the works of the Lord are exceeding good; And he <hi>hath made all things for their uſe,</hi> ſaith the Author of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48506:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſt. Cap.</hi> 39.16, 17, 21. That none might blaſpheme Gods works, as that profane Spaniard did.</p>
               <p>That none might ſpeak or think falſely and fooliſhly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God, as the Jews do, <hi>viz. Deum ultima veſpera prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventum quaedam animantia imperfecta reliquiſſe.</hi> Calvin. in Gen. 2.1.</p>
               <p>God the Judge of Heaven and Earth, did in the beginning of the World ſtrictly look and enquire into, truly try and righteouſly judge all his Creatures; and he returns <hi>Omnia benè,</hi> I find no fault in any thing that I have made. God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving newly printed the Book of the Creatures in ſix days, and having compared it ſheet by ſheet (as it were) before, with the original in his own mind, and found no fault in it; he doth now again that the whole work is finiſhed, read it and examine all over again, and ſees no jota or tittle amiſs in it from the beginning to the end thereof; no place for the leaſt daſh of the pen of Men or Angels, and no need of the leaſt touch of his own hand, either to correct or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat it.</p>
               <p>And this brings us to the other Obſervation, that it was a true and righteous judgment which God paſſed upon his Creatures, as they came out of his hands at firſt, that they were very good. They were <hi>good</hi> before, and well approved of, four or five times, by God; but now that all is done and poliſhed by God's own hand, now 'tis perfect, <hi>very good;</hi> nothing need to be added thereunto. When God ſaw the parts of this body of the Univerſe part by part, each was good and beautiful as he made and viewed it day by day: But now the body being fully compleated, by that which every part ſupplyeth; and now this body of the viſible World being headed with a viſible head, Man, God's Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Vice-roy, made and ſet to rule and govern all his Creatures here below; Now 'tis added, they were <hi>very good.</hi> God aſſembled the Creatures before <hi>Adam,</hi> to ſee what names he would give all his Subjects; and <hi>Adam</hi> gave names to all Cattel, and to the Fowls of the Air, and to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Beaſt of the Field, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Adam</hi> gave them every one his name; and God gave them all an Epithit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, <hi>very good.</hi> I
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48506:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſhall endeavour, with Gods leave and help, to ſhew,</p>
               <p n="1">1. How, and in what ſenſe, the Creatures may be ſaid to be good and very good.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To prove, that the Creatures are ſo very good.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether all the Creatures have always been, and now are ſo very good, as when they firſt came out of God's hands; and, if not, then</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether ever there has been, or ſhall be, a reſtauration of the Creatures to their primitive goodneſs?</p>
               <p n="5">5. What God requires that we ſhould contribute to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the repair of this great Houſe of the World, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the reſtoring the Creatures to their firſt goodneſs and beauty.</p>
               <p>Of the Firſt:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Creatures are all good <hi>Metaphyſically,</hi> as they had a being, <hi>Ens &amp; bonum convertuntur:</hi> And ſo they were drops of that Ocean of goodneſs that is in God. 'Tis good by ſome participation of his goodneſs, and conformity to his Word and Will, without which it could not have been at all. So the Scripture teſtifieth, that <hi>every Creature of God is good,</hi> here, and in the 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4. All that was made was every way agreable to his Will, and contrary to, or without that was nothing made that was made.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Creatures were all good <hi>Morally.</hi> There was no Anomy or Ataxy amongſt them all. Nothing prejudicial to God's glory; and, every thing ſerviceable for mans benefit. The Creatures were good; that is were <hi>goodly,</hi> fair, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to the eyes; Again, they were good; that is, <hi>profitable,</hi> or commodious: So the word may import; for that which one Evangeliſt calleth <hi>good,</hi> Mar. 9.42. another calleth <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable,</hi> Luk. 17.2.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They were <hi>Theologically</hi> good. They were as ſo many Letters, out of which men might ſpell the Name of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. Yea from theſe Creatures, as from ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Teachers, men might learn many profitable Leſſons, touching ſervice and obedience to their Maker. The Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures proclaim to us God's goodneſs, and glory: and again, the homage and duty, which we owe unto God our Creator.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48506:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The Creatures are a kind of Ladder, whereby we may always aſcend up unto God. The World is <hi>Templum Dei,</hi> God's Temple: and <hi>in this Temple doth every one</hi> of his Creatures <hi>ſpeak of his honour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the Second, we ſhall endeavour to evidence the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and beauty of the Creation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. From the various Natures of the Creatures.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From the goodly Order of their creation, propagation, and working.</p>
               <p n="3">3. From their great Uſefulneſs, and ſerviceableneſs unto Man.</p>
               <p n="4">4. From their extraordinary Obedience unto God, their Maker.</p>
               <p>Of the Firſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Every Creature of God is good; and it is a pleaſant thing to behold or conſider the beauty of them all in their firſt creation. How much are we delighted with a good Proſpect, yea with a fair Landskip ſometimes. The ſhew which the Devil tempted our Saviour withal (for, from the top of an exceeding high Hill, he ſhewed him all the Kingdoms of the World, and the glory of them) was of it ſelf a tempting, and would have been a raviſhing ſight to us. But alas! this ſight was nothing, to that view, which God took of all the Creatures of the World, and the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of them.</p>
               <p>Let's behold God's ſix days works, beginning from the Angels in Heaven, to the meaneſt Creature on the Earth, or in the Waters: and we ſhall ſee a delightful ſight, rendred ſo by the excellent variety of the Creation. Some Creatures, as Angels, are all ſpirit, and no bodies: Some again, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Creatures, and no ſpirits: Some half the one and half the other; as Man. Again, ſome Creatures have life; and ſome are without life: Of thoſe that have life, ſome are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, ſome are irrational; Of unreaſonable Creatures, ſome are <hi>integra Animalia,</hi> ſome <hi>Inſecta;</hi> and of both ſorts, ſome live in the Air, and ſome in the Water, and ſome on the Earth, and ſome are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as Crocodils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which live partly in the Water, and partly on the dry Land. Again,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48506:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
there is a Creature which is partly a Plant, and partly an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimal; and that is a Sponge; and, what if we ſay the ſame of the ſenſitive Plant? Come we to inſtance only in the bruit Creatures, and there we ſhall ſee an admirable variety. God hath not fill'd the World with all great, or all ſmall, or all of a middle ſize; but with ſome of every ſort. I ſhall be beholden to the Naturaliſt <hi>(Franzius)</hi> to ſhew a five-fold obſervable Variety amongſt theſe; And this is our Firſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. God their Maker hath ſet to all their ſeveral quantities, their bounds, which they ſhall not paſs. The greedy Swine ſhall never grow to be ſo big as the Elephant; nor the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon to be ſo great as the Swan.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They have their ſeveral Voices and Tones; the Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kow doth never crow like the Cock; nor the Lyon grunt like the Hog; nor the Dog neigh like the Horſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They have their ſeveral Trades and Imployments; The Birds, Nightingals excepted, ſing not in the night; but the Dogs bark in the night, and this Creature alone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trays the Thief, at what hour of the night ſoever he comes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They delight in a diverſe kind of Dyet, feed on ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Diſhes, and God gives every one his proper Diſh, his Meat in his ſeaſon; The Sheep doth not feed on fleſh; nor doth the Horſe take pleaſure to gnaw the bones like the Dog; nor the Fiſh to eat hay like the Oxe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They have ſeveral Dwellings or Hiding-places; The Hare does not lye down at the Crib; nor doth the Dog delight conſtantly to abide in the Wood, amongſt Wolves, Tygers, and Lyons.</p>
               <p>Of the Second.</p>
               <p>God firſt made the Dwelling-houſes of the Creatures, before the Inhabitants thereof; yea he firſt furniſhed and ſtored thoſe ſeveral Manſions of the Creatures, before he made and brought the Creatures into them.</p>
               <p>Firſt, God made the graſs for the Beaſts, and then the Beaſts themſelves. Firſt the inferior Creatures, and then Man the Epitome, &amp; under God, ſupream Lord of all. Firſt, God made Vegetative Creatures, then Senſitive, and then Rational. Firſt the ſimple bodies, as the Elements, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48506:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
then compound; and there firſt a being, without life; then a being and life, without ſenſe; then a being, life, and ſenſe, without reaſon; then altogether, all in one; and that is Man.</p>
               <p>Again, goodly was the order which God ſet for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the Creatures. He gave them a ſeed, whereby to beget others in their own likeneſs; Or, from whence ſhould grow alway another to continue and repleniſh the World.</p>
               <p>It is admirable to think, that ſo much ſhould come of ſo little; that the ſeed of Plants is not quickned except it dye; that when ſeed is ſown in the Earth, the ſeed ſhould grow and ſpring up, and the Sower knoweth not how; For, <hi>The Earth bringeth forth fruit of her ſelf; firſt the Blade, then the Ear, then the full Corn in the Ear,</hi> Mar. 4.27, 28. And all this comes from the goodneſs and bleſſing of God upon it in the firſt Creation. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.11, 12.</p>
               <p>Again, it had been a goodly pleaſant ſight, to have ſeen the Waters bring forth Fiſh and Fowl of themſelves firſt; and ſo the Earth, to bring forth Beaſts, and all kind of Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel after their kind, and all at God's Word of Command at firſt. And that all theſe Creatures ſhould have virtue to multiply, and increaſe, and to repleniſh the Sea, and the dry Land; this is very wonderful.</p>
               <p>This is a goodly order too that God hath ſet; namely, that ſenſitive Creatures ſhould ſome bring forth living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; ſome, egs only; that the Oſtrich ſhould bring forth egs, and leave them; And yet God take order with the Beams of the Sun (as with his wings) to keep them warm and hatch them; That God ſhould ſeed the young Ravens, when they cry, and the old one, the Dam, hath left them; <hi>viz.</hi> (as ſome tell us) by cauſing a little worm to grow out of the dung in the neſt and to crawl into their very mouths to feed them.</p>
               <p>Again, that the great Creatures are not ſo fruitful as the ſmall; and that the wild beaſts do not ſo multiply, as the tame, and more uſeful Creatures do; this is alſo admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. That the Waters, greater than the Earth, and, at firſt,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48506:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
above the Earth, ſhould not overflow it; but be bound in by a girdle of Sand, and that a light body which the wind can blow too and fro where it liſteth. That the Fire doth not conſume and devour all the other corporal Creatures. That the Beams of the Chambers of the World ſhould be laid in the Waters,<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.3.</note> and yet not be moved. That the Globe of the Earth and Waters, ſhould hang upon its own Center only, like a ball in the air; this is indeed wonderful.</p>
               <p>Again, a moſt beautiful ſight it is to behold and conſider, the good order and concatenation of Cauſes, firſt ſet by God. God appointed the Heavens, to hear the Earth; and the Earth to hear the Corn, and the Wine, and the Oyl; and theſe to hear <hi>Jezreel.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.22.</note> This is that ſight which the poor Heathens had ſome glimps of in the night of Gentiliſm; as appears by that Poetical Fancy, of the chain faſtned to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi>'s Chair, and reaching down to the Earth. What ſhould we ſay more? When God finiſhed the Heavens, and the Earth, and all the Hoſt of them; he left them like a well govern'd Army ſtanding in Battel-aray, every one ſet in his rank, every one ordered to march on in his way, and none to break their ranks, no one to thruſt another. So that if the greatneſs and glory of King <hi>Solomon,</hi> and the goodly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his Houſe, or Court, was a ſight which put the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> to an extaſy; what a ſight had it been to have been with <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe, and to have ſeen the general muſter of the Creatures before him, that he ſhould give them their names; and to have ſeen that excellent order, which was obſerved in this great Houſe of the World, and in all the Family of Heaven and Earth; when God looked upon them all, and behold they were very good. Surely a far greater ſight, than that of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Court, was here; for a greater than he hath ſaid,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.29.</note> 
                  <hi>That Solomon in all his glory was not arayed like one of theſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the Third.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Creatures are very good, becauſe they are very uſeful to us. In the ſtate we are now, ſome are for food, ſome for Phyſick, ſome for defence, ſome for covering, ſome for ornament, ſome for our ſervice, ſome for our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48506:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and recreation. To inſtance in ſome particulars.</p>
               <p>The Heavens were made, ſpread out, and garniſhed, for Mans benefit, and advantage. Every Man has his portion in the Stars of Heaven,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.19.</note> as well as in the clods or glebe of the Earth. For, as God hath determined to all Nations, and perſons the bounds of their habitations on the Earth; ſo hath he divided unto them all, the Sun, Moon, and Stars of Heaven.</p>
               <p>The third Heaven is the Seat of the Bleſſed, the Recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle and Manſion of Saints and Angels, the Palace and Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> and his Seed. The viſible Heavens compaſs the World as a glorious wall of fire, are a goodly Mount and fence, yea a goodly covering and canopy to the ſublunary World and to the Inhabitants thereof; The Sun, Moon, and Stars, diſtinguiſh Times and Seaſons, ſeparate Day and Night, give light to the Inhabitants of the Earth, render it fruitful by their heat and influences.<note place="margin">Job 38.31.</note> The Meteors in the middle region of the Air, Fire and Hail, Snow and Vapour, ſtormy Winds, Thunder and Lightening, the ſmall Rain, and the great Rain of his ſtrength; theſe all ſet forth the Power of God, are good for the Earth and the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof, they all fulfil his Word, and this Word of his, that <hi>Lo, he beheld them, and they were very good.</hi> How doth the Snow, though cold of it ſelf, yet keep the Fruits of the Earth warm, like Wool; <hi>He giveth Snow like Wool.</hi> How do the Winds, as God's Beſom, ſweep the Air, and carry about the Clouds which are his Chariots; though theſe Chariots of God are twenty thouſand, even a thouſand thouſand of them, yet all theſe move very ſwiftly upon the wings of the Wind.</p>
               <p>Come we to the lower region of the Air, and there to the Fowls of Heaven. Their flight above the Earth, being made moſt of earth and water, is very admirable; The O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrich doth partly go and partly fly, makes uſe both of her legs and wings; and ſo (they ſay) moves as ſwift as if ſhe did ſly. The very feathers and wings of the Birds are of goodly ſight; <hi>Gaveſt thou the goodly wings to the Peacock?</hi> Job 39.13. Beſides the Fowls are of uſe, ſome for food, ſome for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48506:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
phyſick, ſome for our recreation; Even the very Swallow and the Bat (ſome may think uſeles Creatures) do the one by day, and the other at even, purge the Air of Flyes. The Crows, Ravens, and Eagles, devour thoſe dead Carkaſes which lye on the Earth, and elſe might corrupt the Air, and make it peſtilential. The Crows pick up the Worms after the plough, and ſo better the ſoil; Some Birds are meat for the reſt, and they again for us.</p>
               <p>Come we to the Beaſts of the Field, God hath put all theſe into our hands,<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.7.</note> yea under our feet. The Horſe, and the Cow; Creatures of great, and ordinary, or daily uſe; God hath not given them ſo great galls as to other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, leſt being much uſed, or miſuſed by us, they ſhould wax angry, and turn again, and rent us. The Horſe doth not bite, or kick his Keeper, when he gives him chaff inſtead of provender. The Beaſts are for our food, or phyſick, or for the food of other Beaſts, who are uſeful or ſerviceable to us, either to our neceſſities, or our delights; Even venomous Creatures themſelves, the Phyſicians make good uſe of; &amp;, they ſay, theſe pick up or ſuck up poyſon, which is ſcattered up and down the Earth; and make the places, where they are, more wholſom. Again ſome of thoſe poyſonous Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are meat for other Creatures, which are good food for us; as Hens pick up Spiders, and yet yield us good nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Beſides, it may be queſtioned whether there were any ſuch thing as poyſon before Sin came and brought it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World; we find no Antipathy then betwixt the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and the Serpent; and ſo, poſſibly, no venom neither in the Serpent, until the Devil, that great Poyſoner, poſſeſſed it; however, poyſons ſhould not have been hurtful. As for Flyes and creeping Things, theſe are many of them for phyſick, ſome for food, ſo ſome ſort of Locuſts and Snails; for our ſport ſome; with theſe other Creatures are fed, and ſome taken, as the Fiſhes. Of what admirable uſe are theſe to us; to the Silk-worm, we owe our ſoft rayment; and to the Coche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al, our ſcarlet-dy.</p>
               <p>And as for the Air it ſelf, 'tis a fit <hi>Medium</hi> for us to breathe in, to move in, to derive the influences and light of Heaven to us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:48506:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Come we to the Earth; our Bodies are made of it; we dwell therein; It brings forth Graſs, and Fruits; and ſo, food for us, and the other Creatures; It is our Bed, to ſleep in after death. In the Earth; the Valleys and Plains, are ſit conveyances of water, to water the Earth; are very fruitful, <hi>ſtand ſo thick with Graſs and Corn, that they ſing and ſhout for joy.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 65.13.</note> The Mountains are a ſhadow againſt the ſtorm and heat; they are for the graſing of the Cattel; and thence we have our moſt goodly proſpects.</p>
               <p>Come we to the Waters; there Fiſh are uſeful to us, for food, or delight, or for other uſes. The Waters themſelves yield matter of Rains, and Dews, to refreſh the dry and thirſty ground; ſerve to waſh us, and refrigerate us, or to refreſh us. The Ebbing and Flowing of the Seas prevent the corruptions of the Waters; is very uſeful for ſpeedy tranſportation of Men, and Merchandize, and of the beſt Merchandize, the Pearl of price.</p>
               <p>And now if after all this, there be yet any doubt or ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple concerning the goodneſs of God's Creation, or his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: I anſwer; God knows wherefore he made them all, and to what uſe they ſerve; although we do not. When we come into a Goldſmiths, or other Artificers Shop, and ſee many Tools there, which we know not how to uſe,<note place="margin">In officinâ non aude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vituperare fabrum, &amp; audes in hoc Mundo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendere Deum. <hi>Auſt.</hi>
                  </note> or what they are good for; yet we do not ſtraight way condemn them, as uſeleſs; becauſe the Artificer knows what good uſe they ſerve for. <hi>Neque in poteſtate hominis eſt indagare quam ob cauſam produxerit Natura formicarum alias alis inſtructas, alias abſque alis: Quamobrem etiam vermium alios pluribus pedibus, alios paucioribus produxerit; quiſvè ſit hujus vermis &amp; hujus for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micae finis.</hi> 2. We ſay, that if there be any deformity, at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the whole Creation; if there be any Inſects, or other Creatures, which are noxious; I anſwer this comes from Mans ſin. <hi>Creantur quidem a Deo, ſed ultore;</hi> ſaith <hi>Calvin in Gen.</hi> 2. If Man that was good, and very good, (for, till he was made, God only ſaw, and ſaid of his Creatures that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold they were <hi>good;</hi> but then, <hi>very good;</hi>) prove Apoſtate from God, and Rebel againſt him; no wonder, if God do begin to pull the houſe about his ears. If Man himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48506:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a Briar and a Thorn; no wonder if the Earth bring forth Briars and Thorns to him. Whil'ſt <hi>Adam</hi> continued in his goodneſs, Heaven and Earth was full of God's good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of God's good Creatures. If there be any Creatures which are evil and pernicious to Man, he muſt blame the evil of ſin for that; that is the fly in this Box of Ointment. And yet as things now are, <hi>in ſtatu quo,</hi> we may ſay, as the Son of <hi>Syrach</hi> doth; <hi>For the Good are good things created from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ſo evil things for Sinners.</hi> And a little after, enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome of the principal things for the whole uſe of Mans life; he ſaith, <hi>All theſe things are for good, to the Godly; ſo, to the Sinners, they are turned into evil,</hi> Eccleſ. 39.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And ſo we come to our Fourth Head, or Topick, from whence we are to evidence the goodneſs of the Creatures, namely, their obedience unto their Maker. It may be ſaid of all God's Creatures, as they were made at firſt by him, from the higheſt Angel in Heaven to Man on Earth, and the meaneſt Worm in or under the Earth; that, God command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and they were created, and they rebelled not againſt his Word.</p>
               <p>And now ſince the Angels, ſo many of them, and <hi>Adam</hi> ſell; they from Heaven, and he from Paradiſe; yet the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of the Creatures, even the whole Creation (theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) keep the Law that their Maker ſet them, and are ſtill obedient unto his Word. The Angel deſtroys <hi>Senacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib</hi>'s mighty Hoſt. The Stars in their courſes ſight againſt <hi>Siſera.</hi> The Ravens feed <hi>Elijah.</hi> The dumb Aſs reproves the madneſs of the Prophet. The Frogs and Flyes plague <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> and the Egyptians. The Lice or Worms devour proud <hi>Herod;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aelian. Var. Hiſtor. Lib. <hi>4.</hi> Cap <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> and deſtroy profane and impious <hi>Pherecydes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo we are on a ſudden fallen on an implicite Anſwer to our Third Query, namely, whether the Creatures be all now ſo good as when they firſt came new out of Gods hands. How are the mighty Angels fallen, and become Devils; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of them. And over <hi>Adam</hi> and his poſterity, we may lament, as <hi>David</hi> over <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Jonathan</hi> his Son, a little al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>The beauty of Paradiſe is ſlain upon the high places; How are the Mighty fallen! There the Shield of the Mighty was vilely caſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48506:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
away; The Shield of</hi> Adam, <hi>as if he had not been anointed with the Oyl of</hi> Sanctity and Soveraignty. <hi>How are the Mighty fallen, and the Weapons of war periſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Man that was ſo very good, when God made this general ſurvey of his Creatures, by ſin became ſo very evil, that, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. <hi>God repented and it grieved him at his heart that ever he made him.</hi> How is the goodly Picture, marr'd, the beautiful Face, deformed, the ſweet Inſtrument, broken! <hi>Bethel</hi> made a <hi>Babel,</hi> or a <hi>Bethaven;</hi> Light, become darkneſs; Man that was naturally very good, become by nature very evil. As for the inferiour Creatures; Man's fall exceedingly cruſhed them; yea brought a curſe on his own head, and theirs too: So that, now, they are not generally ſo pleaſant, ſo uſeful, ſo ſerviceable, and obedient to us, as they would have been, if we had not ſinned. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.20.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.20.</note> 
                  <hi>The Creature it ſelf is made ſubject to vanity.</hi> Which place if we underſtand in the moſt ordinary ſenſe, there is a two-fold vanity to which the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are now ſubject; 1. To be abuſed vainly, by ſinful Men, to ryot, luxury, and exceſs; And 2. The Creatures are ſubject to corruption. And thus far we anſwer by way of conceſſion; that the Creatures are not ſo very good as they were at firſt. But yet we ſay,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Creatures are ſtill good in reſpect of their eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, or being, which they have from God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. With the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4. <hi>That every Creature of God is good, and nothing to be refuſed if it be received with thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving. To the Pure all things are pure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. And again, <hi>That all things ſhall work together for good,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> 
                  <hi>to them that love God, and are the called according to his purpoſe.</hi> That if they touch any deadly things, they ſhall not hurt them. To them is the promiſe made, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.13. <hi>Thou ſhalt tread upon the Lyon and the Adder, and the young Lyon and Dragon ſhalt thou trample under feet.</hi> Either there ſhall no evil betide us from the Creatures; or, God will turn it unto good to us.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We ſay too, that 'tis good as things now ſtand: 'Tis for the peace and tranquility of the Common-wealth of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that God hath made ſome Creatures inſtrument
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48506:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
wrath and vengeance, upon Diſturbers and publick Enemies; as, in a well-ordered Common-wealth, 'tis good that there be Goals and Gibbets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the terror and puniſhment of Evil-doers.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. And now if any ask me, Whether the wound, which the Creatures got by the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> cruſhing of them, be incurable? waether the Creatures ever yet have had, or ſhall hereafter have, a Reſtauration to their primitive goodneſs and integrity? I anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That when God, the Builder of this great Houſe of the viſible World, had been ſo provoked by his Tenant <hi>Adam,</hi> that he might juſtly have ſworn in his wrath, that he would pull down this Houſe about his ears; and either make a Dung-hill of it, or conſume it, with the Timber thereof, and the Stones thereof: Then the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> he by whom all things were made which were made at firſt; he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſed, ſtep'd in, held the hand of Divine Juſtice, and put under his ſhoulders, to uphold the tottering Creation; He undertook and covenanted to make God full ſatisfaction and reparation; and to eſtabliſh the World again upon its own Baſis; <hi>Reconciling, or making all things meet again,</hi> and ſweetly kiſs each other;<note place="margin">Col. 1.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether they be things in Earth, or things in Heaven.</hi> Thus did Chriſt become ſurety and bound for us, or elſe a writ of execution had been preſently ſerved upon us, and the Creatures under us, <hi>id eſt,</hi> upon us Body and Goods.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When we read that God reprieved <hi>Adam</hi> from execution; and gave him that great Mother Promiſe of the bleſſed Seed; we may rationally ſuppoſe, that he did, in ſome meaſure at leaſt, alleviate or mitigate the juſtly deſerved curſe upon the Creatures for his ſake and cauſe: For if God ſpared not to promiſe us his own Son, and to deliver him up for us all; how ſhould he not with him freely promiſe to give us all things, even all things richly to enjoy? If he will promiſe to give us his Son, the Heir of all things, in Marriage to us; ſurely the Inheritance too, that ſhall be ours. Again, God will not pardon the Principal, Man; and execute thoſe who are inſtruments, rather than Acceſſaries, to wit the Creatures.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:48506:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>3. If we conſult the latter end of the eighth, &amp; the beginning of the ninth Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> we ſhall find that upon <hi>Noah</hi>'s building an Altar, and offering burnt Offerings unto the Lord, after the Flood, God did covenant and promiſe to uphold and eſtabliſh the World, and did renew <hi>Adam</hi>'s for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited Character, by which he made him Lord of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, unto his poſterity: bleſſing and reſtoring <hi>Noah,</hi> and his Sons, and in them, us, in a great meaſure, to that Right and Royalty, which their and our great Grand-father <hi>Adam</hi> had loſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Lord Chriſt, God bleſſed for ever, by being made actually a curſe for us in the fulneſs of time, hath purchaſed and given unto us the uſe of the Creatures as a bleſſing, and hath utterly taken away the partition wall of typical un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, as to many Creatures (which ſtood for a time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Jew and Gentile) and now <hi>every Creature of God is good, being ſanctified by the Word and Prayer;</hi> that is, good Men may now have a good and holy uſe of all God's good Creatures.</p>
               <p n="5">5. We cannot but acknowledge, that the Scriptures of truth, ſpeak of Goſpel-times as of <hi>the World to come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 3.21.</note> Heb. 1. As of times <hi>of Reformation,</hi> Heb. 9.10. As of times <hi>of Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of all things,</hi> according to our laſt Tranſlation; As of <hi>a new Heaven and a new Earth;</hi> And ſometimes, ſince Chriſt, they ſpeak of <hi>New Jeruſalem coming down from Heaven,</hi> Rev. 22. Of the <hi>Paradiſe of God;</hi> of a <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> and of a <hi>Water of Life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 2.7.</note> Rev. 22.12. And this ſeems to be upon the Earth. And 'tis obſerved, that, then and there, the Tree of Life <hi>bears fruit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very month;</hi> which ſome think, is a reſtoring of it to its pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive fruitfulneſs; and, for want of which, ſome think the Fig-tree was curſed in the Goſpel, ſo Mr. <hi>Brightman.</hi> And there are who think that one day <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> now a dead Sea, ſhall again become a fruitful and pleaſant Land; And for this ſee <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.53.55. There are too, who think that the Creatures <hi>waiting, groaning and longing to be delivered into the glorious liberty of the Sons of God,</hi> Rom. 8. doth hint ſome Reſtitution of the Creatures to their firſt good and ſound ſtate. Which whether it do or no, I leave it to you to judge. Only this I ſay, that if the viſible World ſhall
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48506:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
paſs through a purgatory-fire at the day of Judgment, and if it ſhall be continued for the bleſſed Saints to contemplate God's goodneſs therein at firſt, and the glory of Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> who came to repair the ruins which the firſt made; that then it is not improbable, that the Creatures may then attain to their primitive goodneſs. However ſure I am that the Humane Nature is already, in the Perſon of Chriſt, advanced far above what it was in <hi>Adam</hi> at firſt. The firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was of the Earth earthly, the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> was the Lord from Heaven, heavenly: And again, That all thoſe that are Chriſts, are already in part, and ſhall hereafter in Heaven perfectly, be reſtored to the Image of God wherein they were made at firſt; and to a better and more happy eſtate then ever <hi>Adam</hi> had in Paradiſe.</p>
               <p n="5">V. There's one Query more to be briefly ſpoken unto, and then we ſhall have done with the Fifth thing propounded in the beginning of our Diſcourſe, and that is, what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us towards the repair of the ruins of the Creation, to reſtore the Creatures to their primitive goodneſs and beauty. To this I anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That God doth not require, that we ſhould repair the Angelical Nature; that we ſhould pour Wine and Oyl into their wounds, or bind up their bruiſes; their ſtroke is incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, there is no Balm in <hi>Gilead,</hi> no Phyſician for their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe: Only, we muſt, by endeavouring to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, fit our ſelves to fill up thoſe vacant places in the Heavens from whence they fell. God can make of us, if we duly apply our ſelves to him, although we be but earthen Pitchers, Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of Grace, and Veſſels of Glory; Veſſels every way fit for our Maſters uſe, both in Earth and in Heaven.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Col. 3.9, 10</note>2. God doth expect that we ſhould <hi>put off the old Man with his deeds, and put on the new Man which is renewed in knowledge, after the Image of him that created him.</hi> That, being in Chriſt, <hi>id eſt,</hi> being indeed Chriſtians, we ſhould become <hi>new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, be renewed in the ſpirit of our minds,</hi> and <hi>walk in newneſs of life,</hi> that, <hi>as in</hi> Adam <hi>we all dyed,</hi> and became dead in Sins and treſpaſſes; ſo in Chriſt, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and by a lively Faith in him, we ſhould <hi>all be made aliue.</hi> And, becauſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48506:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> was the Son of God by Creation at firſt; that we ſhould all be <hi>Partakers of the Divine Nature;</hi> be <hi>his workmanſhip, created in</hi> Chriſt Jeſus <hi>unto good works;</hi> Live and walk as <hi>the Sons of God;</hi> all as <hi>the Children of the moſt High,</hi> that the Lord may take pleaſure in us again; as he did in <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe, before he ſinned.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We muſt make a good uſe of all God's good Creatures: getting a new right to uſe them, (although the old one be not utterly loſt) and uſing them alway aright, according to the Creators will, and for his glory.</p>
               <p>Many are the good uſes we may make of the Creatures &amp; this Doctrine of the Creatures uſefulneſs and goodneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">U </seg>I</label> Hence we may be informed, that God made not ſin. For all that he made was good; and Sin that is evil, and as Sin, only evil, and that continually. There was no Anomy, or Ataxy, in all God's works; but Sin it ſelf is an Anomy, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Then God is not the Author of this evil and confuſion. This is the Truth we teach in all the Churches of the Saints; and not, as we are ſlanderouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by the Romaniſts, that we ſay, that God is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Sin. God is <hi>Summum Bonum,</hi> yea Goodneſs it ſelf: but Sin is <hi>Summum Malum,</hi> the chiefeſt Evil; and ſo bad, that Hell and the Devil cannot make it worſe. Ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not call it worſe than to call it by an Epithite drawn from its own name, <hi>viz. ſinful Sin.</hi> This calls the Devil Father, and Author. God, the good <hi>Husbandman,</hi> ſow'd nothing but <hi>good Seed in his Field:</hi> 'tis the Devil, <hi>that Enemy,</hi> that <hi>ſow'd theſe tares.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, hence we infer that Sin is very evil; becauſe it hath poyſon'd ſo many good things; yea hath been the cauſe of all evils in the World. For, at the firſt, God made every thing very good. That muſt needs be bitter indeed, which hath imbittered ſo many, and ſo great ſweets. Sin is the great Troubler of the World, this is it which makes God's good things, turn to be evil to us; that curſes our Bleſſings; that makes a Garden of <hi>Eden</hi> a deſolate Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; that turns the World upſide down; and makes that, when <hi>Jeremy</hi> looked upon the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> that Garden
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48506:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of God, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.22, 23. He beheld the Earth, and lo it was a <hi>Tohu <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>abohu,</hi> without ſorm and void; and the Heavens, and they had no light.</p>
               <p>Further hence we may learn, that the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is very good: a Fountain of goodneſs. For God made all good,<note place="margin">Col. 1.16.</note> and he created all things <hi>by Chriſt.</hi> By him, not as a mere Inſtrument, but a Co-worker with him. He is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Creation of God, in this ſenſe alſo. Is there any good in the World, and the Lord Chriſt hath not done it? and he hath done all things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Well; Heaven and Earth are full of the goodneſs of our Lord <hi>Jeſus;</hi> and there's <hi>No Man good, but one;</hi> and that is one who is God and Man, the Man <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, as to information, hence we are taught that the work of Redemption is very good, exceeding good. For this is a better and greater work than that of Creation. If that deſerve thouſands of praiſes, this doth ten thouſands. The ſong of the Lamb is to be a higher Note, than the ſong of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Creation was a work of God's fingers; but in our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption there was put forth the ſtrength of his holy arm; by which he got himſelf, &amp; us the victory. Behold now a <hi>new Heaven, &amp; a new Earth; the light of the Moon is as the light of the Sun, &amp; the light of the Sun is ſeven-fold: Old things are paſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, &amp; all things are become new.</hi> And therefore, if when God <hi>laid the foundation,</hi> the Corner-ſtone of the World, <hi>the Morning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtars ſang together, &amp; all the Sons of God ſhouted for joy;</hi> No marvel now that Chriſt, by whom all things were made at firſt, and who hath reſtored all things, and <hi>redeemed his People to God, by his blood, out of every kindred; and Tongue, and People, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> If, with the Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> Rev. 5.11, 12, 13. We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and hear the voyce of <hi>many Angels round about the Throne, and the Beaſts and the Elders, the number of them ten thouſand times ten thouſand; and thouſands of thouſands, ſaying with a loud voyce, Worthy is the lamb that was ſlain, to receive power, and riches, and wiſdom, and ſtrength, and honour, and glory, and bleſſing; And every Creature in Heaven, and on Earth, and under the Earth, and in the Sea, ſaying, Bleſſing, honour, glory, and power be unto him that ſitteth upon the Throne, and unto the Lamb, for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:48506:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>If God had his Sabbath, to celebrate his work of Creation: good reaſon Chriſt ſhould have his Sabbath, wherein we ſhould commemorate his work of Redemption. And now, this being the Lords day, and our Chriſtian Sabbath, let us do the duty of the day in the ſeaſon thereof. <hi>Bleſs the Lord, O our Souls, and all that is within us bleſs his Holy Name: Forget not all his benefits, who forgiveth all our iniquities, who redeemeth our life from deſtruction, who crowneth us with loving kindneſſes, and tender mercies,</hi> Pſal. 103.1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">U </seg>II</label> I ſhall conclude all with a few words of Exhortation. When God looked upon his works, did he ſee every thing very good? 1. Then let us not cavil or carp at any of all God's works. <hi>Wo to him that ſtriveth with his Maker: Let the Potſherd ſtrive with the Potſherds of the Earth.</hi> Let's not blame, or find fault with God, for any of all his works, either of Creation, or Providence: for God hath made all things well, and he hath made every thing beautiful in his ſeaſon. If any of God's Creatures, or Providences, prove evil and hurtful to us, let's blame our ſelves, let's blame our ſins: <hi>For Sin, that it might appear Sin, worketh death in us by that which is good,</hi> Rom. 7. 2. Let's admire and adore God. Let's bleſs, and praiſe, and magnify him for ever, for all his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: For <hi>his goodneſs is in and over all his works.</hi> Let's have high thoughts of God, and low of our ſelves. And this is the uſe the Prophet <hi>David</hi> makes of this Doctrine, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.147, 148, 149, 150. Yea this is the uſe, which God himſelf would have <hi>Job</hi> make of it, when he preached upon part of this Text, in the 38, 39, 40, 41. Chapters of the Book of <hi>Job.</hi> And let us ſay with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 103. when we take a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey of Gods works, <hi>Bleſs the Lord ye his Angels, who excel in ſtrength, ye Miniſters of his, that do his pleaſure: Bleſs the Lord all his Works in all places of his Dominion, &amp; every one of us: Bleſs the Lord O my Soul.</hi> 3. Let's learn good from the Creatures. God would have us go to ſchool to the Creatures, to learn many good Leſſons from them. He would have the Sluggard go to the induſtrious <hi>Ant, to conſider her ways, and be wiſe.</hi> Thoſe who are ignorant of God their Lord, and feeder, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the bruit Creatures; <hi>For the Oxe knows his Owner,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48506:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and the Aſs his Maſters Crib.</hi> Thoſe who do not, or cannot diſcern the times and ſeaſons, even the times of their Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Prophet would that we go to <hi>the Stork, the Crane, and the Swallow, for all theſe know their appointed ſeaſons.</hi> And becauſe Chriſtians, and Miniſters eſpecially, are ſent out in the World as Sheep among Wolves, Chriſt would have them to be as wiſe as Serpents, and innocent as Doves.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, did God look upon daily, and at the end of the ſixth day again review all his works? Did he examine, judge, and find them all very good? Let us go and do like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: let us imitate God, we cannot have a better prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent or example to follow. Let us, every evening, look back upon the works of the day, and, at the end of the week, upon the works of the week. Let's examine and judge them. This has been the practice of many precious Saints, as the Lord <hi>Harington,</hi> Mr. <hi>Herbert Palmer,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. (Yea, ſome ſuch thing as this, <hi>viz.</hi> calling himſelf to an account at night, for what had paſſed him in the day, <hi>Seneca</hi> tells of himſelf.) Theſe examples we ſhall do well if we follow, ſo as they followed God himſelf. This is a right method to proceed, from good, to very good; to have all good, but our latter work better than our former. But, becauſe that in many things we offend all, whil'ſt we are in this World here upon Earth, let us look for, and long after, that place and ſtate, I mean for Heaven, when we ſhall be made like unto God, and our works like his works: When from day to day, and Sabbath to Sabbath, even to all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, we may look upon every thing that we have done, and behold it ſhall be very good.</p>
               <trailer>The END of the firſt Sermon.</trailer>
            </div>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:48506:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Proverb. 20.10.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>The righteous Man regardeth the life of his Beaſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ACcording to the Hebrew 'tis, <hi>A righteous Man knows,</hi> that is, regardeth, taketh care <hi>of the life of his Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If on the one hand we conſider the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, which the Holy Scriptures give of diverſe of the bruit and unreaſonable Creatures, together with God's great care of, and coſt, about them, himſelf, and his charge, and laws to Men, concerning them: And on the other hand compare therewith Men's vilifying, diſregard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, abuſing of them: It may ſeem not unreaſonable nor unprofitable to beſtow one lecture about them, namely for this end, to inſtruct and teach Men, who have a right to uſe them, how to uſe them aright, to make them good Lords to thoſe good Servants. As he that rules over tnen muſt be juſt, ſo he that is Lord over theſe bruit Creatures muſt not be cruel towards them. As God will require the life of a Man of the Beaſt that ſlayeth him,<note place="margin">Gen. 9.5. Ex. 21.29.</note> the Beaſt ſhall be put to death. So will God call Men to accompt for the lives of their Beaſts, if they be cruel unto them. For my own part, I would not when my Lord cometh, be found cauſeleſly, or cruelly beating, or miſuſing theſe my Servants and my fellow Servants.</p>
               <p>From the words we may obſerve,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Man hath a Right and Title to the Beaſts of the Earth; and that not only in common, but each Man hath a particular Right and Propriety in them. <hi>The righteous Man regardeth the life of his Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:48506:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>2. That a good or righteous Man is good or merciful to his Beaſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That unrighteous or wicked Men are unmerciful or cruel to their Beaſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">I. Pſal. 8.6, 7.</note>Of the Firſt. God the ſoveraign Lord of Heaven and Earth, the Maker of Man and Beaſt, hath made him Lord over the Beaſts; he hath put them all under his hand, or under his feet.<note place="margin">Gen. 1.25.26, 28.</note> He that made the Beaſt of the Earth after his kind, and Cattel after their kind, made Man alſo after his own Image, and gave him dominion over the Fiſh of the Sea, and over the Fowl of the Air, and over the Cattel, and over all the Earth, and over every living thing that moveth upon the Earth. God indeed made theſe Creatures, and all things elſe, for his own glory; but in order thereunto he made theſe to be our Servants:<note place="margin">Gen. 2.19, 20.</note> And therefore we find that God aſſembled before <hi>Adam</hi> all the Beaſts of the field, to ſee what he would call them;<note place="margin">Gen. 5.2. Luk. 1.62, 63.</note> And his giving Names to them, was a part and proof of his Dominion or Lordſhip over them. At firſt 'tis thought, that Mans Dominion over the Creatures, the Fiſhes of the Sea (the great Whales not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) and over the Fowls of Heaven, was like that of the <hi>Centurion</hi> which he had over his Souldiers: He might ſay to one <hi>Go and he goeth, and to another Come and he cometh, and to a third Do this,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 7.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and he doth it.</hi> They were all ready to come and go at his word of Command: And this was the Language of their Obedience to <hi>Adam</hi> their Lord, Lo we are all thy Servants. Before Sin came into the lower World, <hi>Adam</hi> commanded without rigour, and they obeyed with obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial reverence and readineſs, without the leaſt force or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion. And ſince the fall, God, hath (in a great meaſure) renewed our forfeited Charter, and Men have been able by force or art to ſubdue and govern over the greater &amp; wilder ſort of Beaſts, ſuch as Elephants, Lyons, Leopards, Bears, Tygres,<note place="margin">Plin. Hiſt. B. 8. C. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Elephants have been brought ſo far under Mans yoke, as to be yoked together to draw a Chariot, and in ſome places to draw the Plough, if we will believe <hi>Pliny.</hi> But behold a more ſure word of Prophecy, St. <hi>James</hi> tells us <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>V.</hi> 7. That <hi>every kind of Beaſts, and of Birds, and of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48506:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Serpents, and things in the Sea, is tamed, and hath been tamed of mankind.</hi> As if he had ſaid, It was not ſo only before the Fall; or by miracle, as the Whale not hurting <hi>Jonah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jonah 2. Dan. 6.</note> but caſting him up on dry Land; and the Lyons not hurting <hi>Daniel,</hi> though caſt into their Den to be devour'd by them; or that all the Creatures came tamely to <hi>Noah</hi> into the Ark; but as if he had ſaid, Nothing is ſo violent and noxious by Nature, but humane art and induſtry hath made it ſervicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Mans uſe: For inſtances and ſtories, ſaith D. <hi>Manton in Loc.</hi> Interpreters abound in them; How Lyons have been tamed and brought to hunt as Dogs, or draw the Chariot as Horſes, you may ſee <hi>Pliny</hi> in his Natural Hiſtory <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>C.</hi> 16. and <hi>Aelian. Lib.</hi> 15. <hi>C.</hi> 14. How Birds have been taught; you may ſee <hi>Plin. Lib.</hi> 10. <hi>C.</hi> 42. and <hi>Macrob. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Saturnal. C.</hi> 10. Of Elephants, <hi>Lipſius Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 50. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we are told by D. <hi>Cowel,</hi> that wild Beaſts, Birds, Fiſhes, by the Law of Nature, are not the goods of any one particular perſon; yet, he that firſt gets the poſſeſſion of them, by the Law of Nature hath a Title to them. And as for the tamer Creatures, we have a right to them ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, either by Deſcent, as Heirs to our Parents; or by Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as free gift; or by purchaſe; or elſe as found when loſt, or gotten in, or by means of a lawful War from an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy. And ſo it may be ſaid of any particular perſon, though but a private Man, (who is by any of theſe lawful means, Poſſeſſour of the Beaſts) as God ſaith of King <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 27.5, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>I have given him the Beaſts of the Field alſo to ſerve him.</hi> For God made the Earth, the Man and the Beaſts, that are upon the ground, by his great Power, and his ſtretched out Arm; and giveth it to whom it ſeemeth meet unto him. Though God be the ſoveraign Lord of Heaven and Earth, and all that therein is, yet the Earth hath he given to the Children of Men. He made Man to have dominion over the works of his hands; <hi>He hath put all things under his feet;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 8.7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>All Sheep and Oxen, yea and the Beaſts of the Field; the Fowl of the Air, and the Fiſh of the Sea, and whatſoever paſseth through the paths of the Seas.</hi> From God, Lord Paramount of all, we have a good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tle to, and a propriety in, theſe Creatures.<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.3.</note> 
                  <hi>The
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48506:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Oxe knoweth his Owner, and the Aſs his Maſters Crib.</hi> God having granted and thus ſetled property in particular perſons to the Beaſts of the Earth, 'tis not in the power of Men or Devils, but by Gods Commiſſion or Permiſſion (at leaſt) to alter or overthrow it. The Devil could not touch <hi>Job</hi>'s Sheep or Camels, without leave firſt had &amp; obtained. And as for Man God hath made a hedge about every Man's Cattel by the Eighth Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteal;</hi> And to keep him far from ſuch an evil Matter, he forbids in the X. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment ſo much as <hi>to covet or deſire our Neighbours Oxe, or his Aſs, or any thing that is our Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ghbours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now is it ſo, that we have a Right to and Authority over the bruit Creatures, yet let us be cautioned againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing or miſuſing of them. Say not in your hearts, Our Beaſts are our own, who is Lord over us? May we not do what we will with our own? and doth God take care for Oxen? May we not rather wiſh with <hi>Balaam,</hi> that there were a Sword in our hands to ſlay them when they ſtop or ſtart aſide, ſince they are our own? May we not rather ſay to them, <hi>Our Fathers made your yoke heavy, but our little finger ſhall be heavier than our Fathers loins?</hi> To ſuch abſurd and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Men I ſhall oppoſe the reproof, which the Aſs gave to his Maſter <hi>Balaam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 22.28.</note> 
                  <hi>What have I done to thee, that thou haſt ſmitten me theſe three times?</hi> And again the reproof of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, <hi>V.</hi> 32. <hi>Wherefore haſt thou ſmitten thine Aſs theſe three times?</hi> Although God hath given us a Right to the bruit Creatures, and a Dominion over them; yet 'tis with ſubordination to himſelf and his Laws; yet 'tis with certain limitations and reſtrictions. We are Lords over them, 'tis true; but we muſt not play the Tyrants over them. The <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> God's own People, had a good Title to their Beaſts or Cattel, and yet he bound them to their good behaviour towards them by ſundry Laws and Rules in reference to them. They might not deal with them as they pleaſed, as to their meat. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the Cori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. Nor as to their work, neither for the time when they ſhould work, nor for the manner of their working. Thou ſhalt keep the Sabbath-day, that thy Oxe and thy Aſs may rest as well as thou.</hi> And again,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48506:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not plough with an Oxe and Aſs.</hi> God gave Man the Beaſts and other living Creatures for food, but yet with this condition, provided always they did not eat <hi>Membriun de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo,</hi> not like ſalvage. Beaſts tear and eat of living Creatures, whiles the life was in them, but that they ſhould firſt kill them, and pour out their blood before they eat them. <hi>Ariſe, kill, and eat.</hi> Kill firſt, and then eat. Nor were they at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in all things as to their cooking, or dreſſing of them. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſeeth a Kid in his Mothers milk.</hi> God moſt wiſe, moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful would have his People not only abhominate all cruelty to the bruit Creatures, but even to abſtain from all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of it. And that he might teach them mercy by his own example, that they might be merciful to the bruit Creatures as their Father in Heaven is merciful, He ordained them to be offered up upon his Altar, but not till they were firſt ſlain, and their blood in which their life is, was poured out, at the foot of it. God would have no Sacrifice no not of a Beaſt to be burnt alive upon his Altar.</p>
               <p>Accordingly a good Man, who is the Child of God and Image of God, the work of his Heavenly Father he will do; he will be mild, gentle, merciful, not only to Brethren, Neighbours, and Strangers, but even to the bruit Creatures, ſo ſaith the Text, <hi>A good Man, a righteous Man, is merciful to his Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. He takes care of the life of his Beaſts: [<hi>Curat animam ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti ſui,</hi> Vatablus] in providing food convenient for them. He gives them their meat in due Seaſon. They do not wander for lack of meat, nor low or complain for lack of ſodder. What God gives him ſor them, that they gather from his hand. If God ſend a Drought and the Fire burn up or devour the Paſtures of the Wilderneſs, ſo that the Beaſts groan, and the heards of Cattel are perplexed, becauſe they have no Paſture; the righteous Man, their Lord and Maſter, ſympathizeth with them, is grieved for them, and <hi>modo ſuo,</hi> as God for his People, ſo he for his Cattel, in all their afflictions he is afflicted; and therefore when the Beaſts cry unto him, 'tis not in the power of his hand to help them; what doth he but ſtretch out his arms and cry unto God for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48506:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
As 'tis <hi>Joel</hi> 1.19. <hi>O Lord, to thee will I cry, for the Fire hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the Pastures of the Wilderneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. A good or a righteous Man provides Phyſick for them, I mean Remedies for them, means to cure them when they are amiſs. He doth what he can to prevent, or elſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move their ſickneſſes, ails, and maladies. It was a great ſin in <hi>Pharaoh</hi> that he mattered not the threatning, and ſo did not prevent (by letting <hi>Iſrael</hi> go) the grievous murrain on the Cattel in the Field, <hi>upon the Horſes, upon the Aſſes, upon the Camels,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 9.3.</note> 
                  <hi>upon the Oxen, and upon the Sheep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. A good Man provides Harbour for his Cattel accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their condition, againſt the weather. We read of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> that as he built himſelf an Houſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 33.17.</note> ſo he made Booths for his Cattel. Yea when God threatned a grievous hail upon <hi>Egypt,</hi> he commanded them to ſend and gather the Cattel that were in the Field, leſt they ſhould be ſlain with the hail; and the Scripture tells us, <hi>He that feared the Word of the Lord amongſt the Servants of</hi> Pharaoh,<note place="margin">Exod. 9.18 19, 20</note> 
                  <hi>made his Servants and his Cattel flee into the Houſes, and he that regarded not the Word of the Lord, left his Servants and his Cattel in the Field.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. As a good Man takes care for Food, Phyſick, and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for his Cattel, ſo he hath a care not to overwork them. He doth not load, or ride, or drive them beyond what they are able to bear. Hear how careful and tender <hi>Jacob</hi> was not only of his Children,<note place="margin">Gen. 33.13 14</note> but alſo of his Cattel, <hi>My Lord</hi> (ſaith he to his Brother <hi>Eſau) knows that the Children are ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and the Flocks and Herds with young are with me, and if Men ſhould overdrive them one day, all the Flock will dy: Let My Lord, I pray thee, paſs over before his Servant, and I will lead on ſoftly, according as the Cattel that goes before me, and the Children are able to endure,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He takes care that the weak and tame Beaſts be Kept and Defended from the violence of the ſtrong, wild, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.34, 35.</note> So <hi>David</hi> when he kept his Fathers Sheep, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of a Lamb or a Kid, ſlew a Lyon and a Bear.</p>
               <p n="6">6. He ſeeks them, brings them Home, when they have gone aſtray, and have loſt themſelves. So much may be learnt from the Parable <hi>Luke</hi> 15.4. where we read, that he
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48506:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that hath 100 Sheep, if he loſe one, will leave the 99 in the Wilderneſs, and go after that which was loſt, until he find it; and when he hath found it, lays it on his ſhoulders, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing. A good Shepheard will gather his Lambs with his arm, will carry them in his boſom, and will gently lead thoſe that are with young, when they are out of the way, and gone aſtray, unto the Fold and to the Flock. Even <hi>Saul</hi> himſelf when he found a Kingdom,<note place="margin">1 Sam 9 20</note> was buſied in ſeeking his Fathers Aſſes that were loſt.</p>
               <p n="7">7. When he is neceſſitated to kill them, he pitties them and doth that office in mercy. He was a Tyrant that ſaid, he would make his Enemy <hi>ut ſentiat ſe mori:</hi> that he might feel or be ſenſible of dying; And he is but little better that ſhall torment the poor Beaſts, when he puts them to death. A good Man doth not delight in ſlaying the Beaſts, nor doth he ſeek or uſe ways to torment them, 'Tis to the commendation of Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> that wrote the Book of Martyrs,<note place="margin">F. H. Book <hi>9.</hi> pag. <hi>105.</hi>
                  </note> what I read of him in Mr. <hi>Fuller,</hi> namely that he did not uſe to paſs the Slaughter-houſes without ſome ſenſe, grief, or trouble of mind. <hi>Macellum ipſum ubi mactantur etiam pecudes vix praetereo, quin tacito quodam doloris ſenſu mens refugiat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Queſtion then ſhould be, what ſay we to hunting of wild Beaſts? Is this cruelty? And may not a good Man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in ſuch ſport or recreation?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, that ſome of the Ancients held it unlawful. S. <hi>Hierom</hi> obſerves that a Hunter is never taken in a good ſenſe,<note place="margin">In Mich. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> and that <hi>Iſmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> are Hunters. There's a ſaying alſo of S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> on the 102. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> alledged againſt it: <hi>Qui ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natoribus donant, non homini donant, ſed arti nequiſſimae; nam ſi homo eſſet &amp; venator non eſſet, non donares; honor as in eo vitium, non naturam.</hi> But on the other ſide the reverend and learned Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> allows for recreation the hunting of wild Beaſts, alledging that place, <hi>Take us the Foxes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 2.15.</note> 
                  <hi>the little Foxes that ſpoil the Vines.</hi> And another late Writer of Caſes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſaith thus, For exerciſes, ſuch ſhould be choſen, as bring publick utility; as the hunting of ſuch Beaſts, as are an annoyance to the Country; ſuch as Foxes, Badgers, Wolves, <hi>&amp;c. Aquinas</hi> cites <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> for the lawfulneſs of Hunting,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48506:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
upon this ground or reaſon; becauſe thereby a Man chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth to himſelf that he hath a right to, by Nature. <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio Sylveſtrium Animalium eſt juſta &amp; naturalis, quia per eam, Homo vendicat ſibi, quod eſt naturaliter ſuum. Sariburienſis</hi> in his Book called <hi>Policratic.</hi> 500. years ſince, brings <hi>Iſaac</hi> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch his practice in ſending his Son <hi>Eſau</hi> to hunt, to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the lawfulneſs of Hunting.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> A. J.</note> And a late judicious and learned Commentator comparing and conſidering the holy Scriptures one place with another, <hi>viz. Levit.</hi> 17.13. with <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.27. doth thence conclude that Hunting is lawful; the covering of the blood of the Beaſt taken and killed in Hunting, may imply (according to him) the lawfulneſs of killing the Creatures in this manner: the covering of their blood ſignifying that it ſhould not be imputed unto them that ſhed it; as may appear by thoſe places, where the not covering of the blood doth imply the contrary. So <hi>Job</hi> 16. 18. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.7, 8.</p>
               <p>The main Objection I conceive againſt Hunting is this, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Antipathy betwixt the Creatures is uſually reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as an effect and fruit of our Sin, and therefore is not to be delighted in.</p>
               <p>To this Objection I ſuppoſe that Huntſmen may anſwer, that they delight and recreate themſelves in the ſagacity and ſwiftneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of them; and not in their tearing of one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. And if we will believe <hi>Aquinas p.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 96. <hi>Artic.</hi> 1. he teacheth us, that there would have been <hi>naturalis diſcordia inter quaedam Animalia,</hi> a natural diſcord betwixt ſome Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals although Sin had never been. <hi>Non enim per peccatum Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis natura Animaliu eſt mutata. (i. e.)</hi> For the nature of theſe Creatures is not changed by Mans Sin.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.12.</note>Beſides it may be argued and pleaded that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of ſome of thoſe Creatures, that they are <hi>made to be taken and deſtroyed.</hi> And our own reaſon, and ſenſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience teach us, that there are other Creatures who ſeem to be made on purpoſe for this uſe, namely to find out, purſue, and take others.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſing this Antipathy betwixt the Dog and the Hare, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould be a fruit, effect, or conſequent of Mans
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48506:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Sin; I conceive that it doth not neceſſarily follow, that we may not moderately delight in Hunting: for our Clothes are a conſequent of Mens Sin; and yet we may moderately delight in our Clothes or Ornaments,<note place="margin">Iſa. 61.10. Jer. 2.32.</note> I ſuppoſe as well as in our Meat and Drink.</p>
               <p>Theſe things then premiſed, I ſhall not dare to condemn Hunting as unlawful; but ſhall rather apply my ſelf to give ſuch directions and cautions to thoſe that uſe this recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they may not offend in it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Men muſt not make Hunting, Hawking, or any other recreation (how lawful ſoever) their calling; not their Meat and Drink; but as their Sawce both to their meat and to their work to get them a ſtomach to both. Thoſe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly are to be condemned, ſaith learned <hi>Rivet</hi> on <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. <hi>Qui voluptatem venationis praeferunt officiis ſuis, &amp; quid Reipublicae &amp; ſubditis debeant, obliviſcuntur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Men muſt not give all their goods to feed their Hounds, their Hawks, their Horſes, and have no ability or charity to feed the Poor. It was well done of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted a Rent-charge of 24 ſheaves of Oats payable out of every Plough-land betwixt <hi>Trent</hi> and <hi>Edinburgh-Frith,</hi> for the King's Hounds, to his new built Hoſpital in <hi>York;</hi> for though (as the Hiſtorian obſerves) it is not lawful to take the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren's bread and give it unto Dogs;<note place="margin">F. H. b. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note> yet it is lawful to take the Dogs bread and give to the Children.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Men muſt not be lovers of Pleaſure, more than lovers of God, nor let either the cares or pleaſures of the World hinder the profitable and ſaving hearing of the Word of God. 'Tis obſervable, that amongſt all thoſe that made excuſes from coming to the Feaſt when invited, although we find one ſaying, <hi>I have bought a yoke of Oxen, and go to prove them;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lu. 14.18, 19.</note> Another, <hi>I have bought a Form and I go to ſee it, I pray thee, have me excuſed;</hi> Yet I find none ſo hardy, as to ſay I have bought a pack of Hounds, or a caſt of Hawks, and muſt go to prove them, I pray thee have me excuſed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Men muſt not injure or wrong their Neighbours in their Goods, or Lands, or Profits, whil'ſt they follow their own pleaſures. Our Princes, ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi> do grievouſly ſin
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48506:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
with their Hunting; they deſtroy the ſeeds and grounds of poor People; And theſe are to be reproved, ſaith <hi>Rivet</hi> on <hi>Geneſis</hi> 11. <hi>Qui miſellis Ruſticis plagas inferunt, ſata laeta, boumque labores diruunt,</hi> &amp;c. Much more are they to be reproved and condemned that depopulate Towns and Countries to make room for Beaſts wild or tame, Deer or Sheep. 'Tis obſerved in our Chronicles that <hi>VVilliam</hi> the Conquerour did depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulate 30 or more Pariſhes to make his new Foreſt, and that in that Foreſt one of his Sons, namely King <hi>VVilliam,</hi> ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Rufus,</hi> and one of his Nephews or Grand-children, came to untimely ends there.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Men muſt be cautioned to be careful, leſt while they purſue their ſports, their game, they loſe not, or hazard not their own or others limbs or lives. Our own Hiſtories tell us of ſome that ſhot at Beaſts and kill'd Men: So, one <hi>Tyrel</hi> kill'd King <hi>VVilliam Rufus,</hi> &amp; Archbiſhop <hi>A.</hi> the Keeper. And we read elſwhere of <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperour that he broke his ſhoulder in Hunting. If we muſt not be cruel to the bruit Beaſts, then ſurely not to our ſelves, hazarding or expoſing our own lives, whiles we hunt them to death. And this makes way for theſe Third Obſervations, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">III.</note>That wicked or unrighteous Men are cruel, unmerciful to the bruit Beaſts. And this appears in that,</p>
               <p n="1">1. They keep them hardly, provide not carefully and conſcientiouſly Food, Phyſick, Harbour, for their hungry, ſick, and weary Beaſts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They work, drive, lead or burden them immoderatly, and not as they are able to bear.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They will rail at them, be in rage with them, and curſe them bitterly; theſe poor Beaſts which were juſtly curſed for them, are again curſed by them, without a cauſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They will beat and miſuſe them ſhamefully: How oft are theſe poor dumb Creatures beaten cruelly with many ſtripes, and that when they know not their Maſters will, what it is they would have them do! How have I heard wicked Men curſe and ban their Beaſts! How have I ſeen them beat and abuſe them without a cauſe; threatning (with <hi>Balaam</hi>) if there were a Sword in their hand to ſlay
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:48506:19"/>
them! If theſe dumb Creatures ſhould have their mouths opened as <hi>Balaam</hi>'s Aſſe's mouth was; how might they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain and ſay, Wherefore haſt thou ſmitten me, it may be, not theſe three times only, but theſe three-ſcore times! Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though many Men live on the labour and ſweat of their Beaſts; yet they care not in their rage and fury to ſlay them, to ſpill their blood. Well may the whole Creation groan wayting to be delivered from this bondage unto corrupt and cruel Men. How many unreaſonable and cruel Maſters are there, which are like <hi>Pharao</hi>'s Taskmaſters to the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> who required brick and gave them no ſtraw, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of their Beaſts to labour, to travel, to work, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them no meat, or not meat ſufficient! How do Men load their Beaſts, more than they are able to bear, and drive them faſter than they are able well to go; and if they ſtumble, fall down, or ſtand ſtill, how are theſe their Servants beaten, when the fault is in their cruel Task maſters! I confeſs I have often wiſhed, that ſome law might be made for the eaſe of theſe poor Beaſts, even to bind their Maſters to their good behaviour towards them: Good reaſon I think there is, as that he that ſteals his Neighbours Beaſt ſhould be puniſhed, ſo, that he that ſlays his own Beaſt, making it a ſacrifice to his paſſion, madneſs or folly ſhould not eſcape unpuniſhed.</p>
               <p>Hence we may be informed, that although in our days the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>I</label> calling of Shepherds and Herdſmen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be mean and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, yet they are lawful and commendable Callings. The Angels of Heaven though they are above us, both in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and office, yet they are our Miniſters and Servants, <hi>to keep us in all our ways,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 91. Heb. 1.14.</note> 
                  <hi>to miniſter to them that are Heirs of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And ſo Men, though they be above and Lords of theſe Creatures; yet may they attend on them, look to them, and provide for them.<note place="margin">Job 1.</note> As the riches of the Ancients conſiſted moſtly in their Cattel, ſo their imployment was moſtly about them. The Patriarchs were Keepers of Sheep, and they bred up their Sons and Daughters to the ſame Calling. And <hi>Saul</hi> loſt nothing by ſeeking his Fathers Aſſes, for he found a Kingdom whiles he was ſeeking of them. And <hi>David</hi> was taken from following the Ews great with young, and anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48506:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
King over <hi>Iſrael.</hi> God himſelf appeared to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Buſh whiles he was feeding <hi>Jethro</hi>'s Flock; when he was a Shepherd, and not when he was in <hi>Pharao</hi>'s Court, and he made him King in <hi>Jeſurun.</hi> And not only the Poët calls the King <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Shepherd of the People; but the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophets alſo do the like. Yea God himſelf in Scripture is called a Shepherd: <hi>Hear O thou Shepherd of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>thou that leadeſt</hi> Joſeph <hi>like a Flock.</hi> And our bleſſed Saviour as he is King of Kings and Lord of Lords, ſo is he alſo called <hi>the good, the great, and chief Shepherd.</hi> Therefore if there be any Shepherds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that hear me this day, let them go away com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted and incouraged to go on in their callings, therein a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide with God. Conſider that <hi>David</hi> was beloved of God, and pleaſed God, not only when he had a Crown and Scepter, and led his People <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but alſo when he had his Scrip and Shepherds Crook, when he followed the Ews great with young. Art thou a Shepherd? thou art not a foot the farther off from being a Sheep of Chriſt, from Chriſt's fold. Often think whiles you are keeping your Flocks by day, or watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them by night, how the glad Tidings of Salvation, the News of Chriſt's B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rth, was brought by a multitude of the Heavenly Hoſt, the Angels of Heaven, to the Shepherds whilſt they were keeping their Flocks by night, ſaying and ſinging, <hi>Glory be to God in the higheſt, Behold we bring you good tidings of great joy which ſhall be to all People,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 2.</note> 
                  <hi>for unto you is born this day in the City of</hi> David <hi>a Saviour, which is Chriſt the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>II</label> 2. Then let us ſhew our ſelves good Men, righteous Men, let's be merciful, no ways cruel and unmerciful to the bruit Creatures; conſidering,</p>
               <p n="1">(1) Hereby we ſhall ſhew our ſelves merciful as our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in Heaven is merciful; For as he made Man and Beaſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.5.</note> and is the Owner of them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. ſo he preſerveth Man and Beaſt. He provides food convenient for them: Graſs for the Cattel for meat, and Water for them to drink, Water in abundance,<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.10, 11.</note> ſo that <hi>the wild Aſſes,</hi> the moſt thirſty Creatures, <hi>may quench their thirſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2) God would that no Man ſhould do them wrong. He reproved <hi>Balaam</hi> for the Aſſe's ſake;<note place="margin">Jude.</note> the dumb Aſs ſpeaking
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48506:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
with Mans voice, rebuked the madneſs of the Prophet. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum</hi> Balaami <hi>ſemel in omnes aetates os aperuit, ut illo ſuo ſermone damnaret omnem in muta jumenta ſaevitiam,</hi> Ct. in Prov. 12.10. The Aſs opened his mouth once, to teach all Generations to abhor cruelty to the dumb Creatures. Yea,</p>
               <p n="3">(3) 'Tis the will of God, that we ſhould be ſo far from hurting or miſuſing cruelly our own Beaſts, that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to be friendly to our Enemies Oxen or Aſſes, if we find them fallen under their burden we are to help them up.<note place="margin">Ex. 23.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="4">(4) And as God made the Sabbath, that thy Oxe and thy Aſs might reſt as well as thou; So he diſpenſeth with the bodily reſt of the Sabbath to ſhew mercy to the bruit Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. It is lawful to looſe the Oxe or Aſs from the Stall on the Sabbath-day, and to lead them to water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that not only the Prieſts in the Temple break the Sabbath, and are guiltles in ſlaying and offering up the Beaſts in Sacrifice; but Herdſmen and Shepherds, and thoſe that are Keepers of Cattel, that attend upon them, although they break the outward reſt of the Sabbath; yet are they guiltles &amp; blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les in ſo doing for the preſervation of the health or lives of their Cattel: and in this caſe God will have Mercy rather than Sacrifice. We may omit for a time, or give over pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſave the life of a Beaſt,<note place="margin">Acts 20</note> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did his preaching to ſave the life of a Man, of <hi>Eutychus.</hi> Further;</p>
               <p n="5">(5) When God would drown the World for the Sin of Man, and only ſave eight Perſons alive, he took care alſo to preſerve alive by miracle in the Ark, the bruit Creatures as well as Men and Women.</p>
               <p n="6">(6) And after the Flood, God was pleaſed to make a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with the Beaſts of the Field, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as well as with Man,<note place="margin">Gen. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>That he would drown the World no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">(7) Afterwards when God ſpared the great City of <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh,</hi> he is pleaſed graciouſly and mercifully to take notice of the abundance of Cattel in it, that muſt have periſhed in the deſtruction of the City, and he ſpeaks of this as a reaſon or motive to ſpare the City.<note place="margin">Jonah 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If it ſhould be objected; Doth God take care for Oxen?
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48506:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Hath not God oftentimes even devoted the Beaſts as well as their ſinful Maſters, Owners to deſtruction? And doth he not in ſome caſes command the Beaſt to be put to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, and ſo to be ſacrificed to juſtice? And again, Did not God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire under the old Law frequent, yea daily ſacrificing of Beaſts, making the life of the Beaſt to go for the life of a Man? And laſtly as to this Objection, Did not our Saviour permit the Devil to go into the herd of Swine, and ſo they, 2000 of them ran violently into the Sea, and were choked in the Sea?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> [1] I ſay that God hath a ſupreme Right &amp; Title to all the Beaſts of the Fold,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> the Field, or the Foreſt. <hi>All the Beaſts of the Field are mine, and the Cattel upon a thouſand hills.</hi> And that he may diſpoſe of, or do what he will with his own. Who may ſay to him, what doſt thou? That when God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys Mens Cattle, he doth it not out of the leaſt hatred to the Beaſt, but to teſtify his hatred and abhorrence of the Sins of the Owners of them, and hereby to puniſh them; or to bring them to repentance, to melt (or mollify at leaſt) their hard hearts, and cauſe them to ſay as <hi>David, 'Tis I,</hi> or 'tis we, <hi>that have ſinned, theſe Sheep</hi> (or Oxen) &amp;c. <hi>what have they done?</hi> Or to prove and try them, and do them good in their latter end; as was the caſe of <hi>Job.</hi> If God may juſtly puniſh Parents in their Children, becauſe they are their goods; ſurely then he may puniſh Maſters and Owners in their Cattel, becauſe they have a propriety in them; and the taking away the lives or the loſs of their Cattel redounds to them.</p>
               <p>As for the Beaſts that were offered up in Sacrifice by Gods Ordinance and Inſtitution: He might as juſtly do it, as to give Men a Charter or Patent to <hi>Ariſe, Kill, and Eat,</hi> for the preſervation of their natural lives: For by the Sacrifice the Sinner was freed from that temporal death, which the Sin deſerved for which it was offered; And beſides, this Sacrifice was typical of Chriſt <hi>the Lamb of God, which taketh away the Sins of the World;</hi> and ſo was of uſe alſo, to the ſaving of the Soul of the Sinner.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Gergeſens</hi> Swine, I ſay:</p>
               <p n="1">(1) Our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> was Lord of all, and therefore
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48506:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
might juſtly permit or ſuffer the Devils to enter into them, and to hurry them headlong into the Sea.</p>
               <p n="2">(2) Thereby their Owners ſhould have learnt, how good and merciful God was to them, that he did reſtrain the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and not ſuffer him to poſſeſs their whole Country; And that goodneſs and mercy of Chriſt, that whereas there was a Legion of Devils in one Man, he ſuffered them not, when caſt out, to diſperſe themſelves about the Country and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs a Legion of Men, <hi>i. e.</hi> above 6000 Men; but only this herd of Swine.</p>
               <p n="3">(3) Our Saviour teaches us that natural Men value and prefer their Swine before their Saviour.</p>
               <p n="2">[2] Let us conſider, that we may deal merciful with theſe Creatures, that they are Fellow-creatures with us, yea our Fellow-ſervants to the great Lord of Heaven and Earth, as well as they are our Servants, and we Lords over them. And muſt give an account when our Lord Chriſt comes, if he find us beating our Fellow-ſervants, if he find us drinking with the Drunken, and preſently falling upon theſe our Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ſervants.</p>
               <p n="3">[3] As they are our Servants, to conſider that they are good Servants to us, who are too often bad Maſters to them. If we will uſe them, they ſubmit their necks to our yoke; If we abuſe them they do not complain; In their mouth is no reproof. That which uſually inflames Maſters againſt Servants is when Servants will anſwer again; will contradict or at leaſt diſpute it with them: Now theſe our Servants they are mute, dumb Creatures; they cannot plead their own cauſe, they return not a word for a blow, not a word for many blows, though without a cauſe, or a ſufficient cauſe.</p>
               <p n="4">[4] Let us conſider, theſe Creatures were partakers of the curſe of Mans Sin; by reaſon of this <hi>they groan and travail in pain;</hi> their yoke is harder and their burden heavier: We ſhould look on their ſorrows and ſufferings as occaſioned, as merited by us, by our diſobedience to our ſoveraign Lord. How do they ſpend their days in our ſervice! end their lives for our ſervice, for Food, for Phyſick; ſometimes for a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and oftentimes even for a Pleaſure, Delight, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation!
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48506:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
They ſuffer for us; We eat the ſour Grapes, and their Teeth are ſet on edge: and this juſtly too, becauſe they are our proper goods, and we are Lords over them. Many times they ſuffer with us, as in War and other publick calamities; and let this ſuffice, let them never ſuffer unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily from us. If we do, we make them exceeding mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable: the poor abuſed Beaſt hath no knowledge or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of death (as Men in miſery have) to put an end ere long to his bondage and miſery; nor any hopes of a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, or a future reward for his ſufferings (as good Men have) to comfort them. The <hi>Turks,</hi> I read, hold that the Beaſts ſhall riſe again; and although that is no part of my Creed; yet I dare ſay, if they ſhould, they will riſe in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt thoſe that have cruelly uſed them here.</p>
               <p n="5">[5] We may go to ſchool to them and learn many a good Leſſon from them. How great is the love and faithfulneſs of Dogs! the meekneſs of Elephants! the ſhamefaſtneſs of the adulterous Lyoneſs! the chaſtity of the Turtle! the watchfulneſs of the Cock! the utility of the Sheep! 'Tis ſaid of King <hi>Porus</hi> his Elephant, that he expoſed his own life to ſave his Maſters. How often doth the Holy Ghoſt ſend us to ſchool to the unreaſonable Creatures! <hi>Go to the Ant, thou Sluggard, conſider her ways, and be wiſe.</hi> Thoſe who do not know God that hath nouriſhed and brought them up, how are they reproved by the Oxe and the Aſs! <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. <hi>The Oxe knoweth his Owner, and the Aſs his Maſters Crib: but Iſrael doth not know; my People doth not conſider.</hi> Thoſe which know not the day of their Viſitation, may go to ſchool to the Crane &amp; Swallow, who know their appointed ſeaſons. Thoſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren who are without natural affection to their aged Parents, let them go to the Stork, and learn of that Creature to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite their Parents <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to feed their Parents when they are old.</p>
               <p n="6">[6] Conſider, that if we be Friends with God, the very Beaſts themſelves are not only our Servants, but our Friends alſo. Our Lord <hi>Chriſt hath reconciled all things in Heaven and Earth.</hi> Whiles we were Rebels and Traitors to God our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, the Angels of Heaven, and the Beaſts of the Earth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48506:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
became Enemies to us, and in purſuit of their allegiance were ready to fight againſt us; but now being reconciled to our Soveraign, and returned to our obedience, theſe our Fellow-ſubjects are again at peace and friends with us. When articles of peace are made with the General of an Army and publiſhed, none of the Souldiers dare act any hoſtility againſt us. The Lord of Hoſts hath now made a Covenant, <hi>viz.</hi> of peace for us <hi>with the Beaſts of the Field,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.18.</note> 
                  <hi>and with the Fowls of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and with the creeping Things of the ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">[7] Conſider, that we ſtand in more need of God's mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy than the bruit Creatures do of ours. We have ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, which theſe Creatures never did. Man being in honour, underſtandeth not,<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.20</note> but is compared to the Beaſt that periſheth. 'Tis no Sin to be a Beaſt, but 'tis a great Sin to be like a Beaſt. And yet which of us, but hath cauſe ſometime or other, not only to confeſs with <hi>Agur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 30.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Surely I am more brutiſh than any Man, I have not the underſtanding of a Man;</hi> but alſo with <hi>David, So fooliſh was I, and ignorant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.22</note> 
                  <hi>and even as a Beaſt before thee.</hi> We read that all manner of Beaſts have been tamed by mankind, but yet the ſame Scripture tells us to our ſhame, <hi>The Tongue can no Man tame,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jam 3.7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>'tis an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly evil, full of deadly poyſon.</hi> And hence we may learn, that we ſtand in need of more mercy from God, than theſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are able to receive from us, or we to give them. For we ſtand in need not only of temporal mercies as they do, but even of ſpiritual mercy, of grace to pardon us, and of grace to reform us, and over and above of eternal mercy, or elſe we ſhall be more miſerable than the Beaſt that periſheth; For as a Reverend Author ſaith, when a Dog dyeth, there's an end of all his miſery; but when a Man dyes (that is, that lives and dyes in his Sin) there's the beginning of his wo. And ſo much for the conſiderations that ſhould move us to ſhew mercy to the bruit Creatures. I ſhall in the next place lay down ſome cautions for the regulation of our kindneſs to them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let us take care that as we do not depreſs theſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures too low, ſo that we do not advance them too high: as we muſt not deſpiſe them in any degree, ſo we muſt not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48506:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
deify them in any wiſe: As we muſt not tear and worry them without a cauſe, ſo not worſhip them for any cauſe. We muſt not <hi>change the Glory of the incorruptible God into an Image made like</hi> (as, not to corruptible Man, ſo) <hi>to Birds, and four-footed Beaſts, and creeping Things.</hi> We muſt not be Devils, Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to them; nor make them Gods to us, ſo as to fall down and worſhip them; as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> did to <hi>Apis,</hi> from whence the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> learnt to worſhip the golden Calf.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As we muſt not adore them as Gods, ſo neither make them our equals. We muſt take heed of too much fondneſs of them, or familiarity with them. Hence comes that Sin, wich the Scripture calls <hi>Confuſion,</hi> viz. Beſtiality, a deſcent nearer Hell by one degree, than the Sin of <hi>Sodom;</hi> which brought a kind of Hell, <hi>viz.</hi> Fire and Brimſtone out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon them. And yet ſome have conjectured, that ſome ſort of Creatures have come into the World this way, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their great likeneſs to Men. <hi>Monſieur de la Chambre</hi> tells us that there have been Beaſts diſcovered, which are ſo like Men, that there is ſcarce any difference as to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward form. And I read in <hi>Mercator's Geography</hi> in his Deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of <hi>Ireland, pag.</hi> 48. of a Lake there, about 30 miles in length and 15 in breath, of which, thoſe that live near it, ſay, it was formerly inhabited, <hi>&amp; Agrum fuiſſe cultiviſſimum,</hi> but for the Sin of Beſtiality was turn'd into a Lake, <hi>ſuperfuſis aquis in Lacum redactum.</hi> If ſo, their Sin being worſe than the Sin of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> no marvel if their puniſhment was ſomewhat like theirs that were turned into a bituminous Lake, or a dead Sea, and remain ſo to this day.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Much leſs muſt we prefer them before Men: We muſt not be cruel to Men pretending to ſhew mercy to the bruit Creatures. The life of a Beaſt muſt go ſtill, to ſave or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the life of a Man. I cannot but condemn the <hi>Turks,</hi> who ſet Birds at liberty out of their Cages, redeeming with money theſe Captives, and yet make no conſcience of chain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians to their Galleys; As alſo the hypocriſy, that cheat amongſt the Romaniſts, whoſe Clergy are forbid to hunt Beaſts, and yet ſome made Lords Inquiſitors on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to hunt down, tear, and devour the harmles Sheep and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:48506:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Lambs of Chriſt. Surely the good, the great, and the chie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Shepherd of the Flock, and the Biſhop of our Souls will count them but little thanks for their ſo doing, when he ſhall come to hold his general Viſitation, and to judge the World. Theſe things notwithſtanding, I dare not condemn thoſe (if neceſſitated to ſave and defend their own lives) which in the Civil Wars of <hi>France</hi> cut off their Horſe-legs, and ſo made themſelves a breaſt-work of their bodies. Nor dare I judge King <hi>David</hi> for houghing his Enemies Horſes, thereby to make them unſerviceable for the Wars, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.4. Let's not be ſuperſtitiouſly afraid to uſe theſe Creatures, either for Food, Phyſick, or Service, no nor for our honeſt Delight and Recreation. See your Charter for ſo doing, if not impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citely given to <hi>Adam,</hi> yet expreſly to <hi>Noah;</hi> and again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed <hi>Act.</hi> 10. under the Goſpel, in the Viſion and Voice to <hi>Peter, Ariſe</hi> Peter, <hi>Kill, and Eat.</hi> And though 'tis ſaid, the Diſciples of the <hi>Nazarites</hi> may be known by their abſtinence from the fleſh of all living Creatures;<note place="margin">Gen. 9.</note> yet our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> and he that in ſubſtance though not in vow and ceremony was the true <hi>Nazarite,</hi> gave his Diſciples no ſuch Commandment. Thoſe who refuſe altogether to eat the fleſh of living Creatures, when duly kill'd, deſerve the name of <hi>Pythagoreans,</hi> Followers of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> the Philoſopher, rather than to be called Chriſtians, or Diſciples of Chriſt our Saviour. So then, uſe theſe Creatures we may, we muſt, without ſcruple, for our meat; yea and we may uſe theſe Creatures for our work, to plow and harrow the Ground, and to carry our Corn into the Barn, and for any other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary uſe. And although many condemn thoſe Perſons who promote the generation of Mules, ſo doth <hi>Maimonides</hi> in his <hi>More Nev. p.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. and our own Writers on <hi>Gen.</hi> 36.24. Yet we may uſe them lawfully; for we find them brought to <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 King. 10.25. 2 Chron. 9.24. and amongſt the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> at their return from captivity, <hi>Ezra</hi> 2.66. and <hi>Nehem.</hi> 7.68. And we no where find that ever they were commanded to put theſe away, though Monſters in Nature, as they were to put away their outlandiſh Wives.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Then hence may be condemned the horrible cruelty
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:48506:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of the old Sicilian Tyrants;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phalaris,</hi> &amp;c.</note> of the Roman Emperour <hi>Caligula,</hi> who was called for his cruelty, <hi>Lutum ſanguine maceratum,</hi> dirt or clay ſoaked in blood; and of the reſt; as alſo of the Popes of <hi>Rome;</hi> The firſt ſort againſt Men, the ſecond againſt Chriſtians, the third againſt Proteſtants, or ſuch as concurr'd in Doctrine or Tenets with them. The truth is, <hi>Rome</hi> was, and is, a bloody City, and well ſet out in the <hi>Revelations</hi> by <hi>a Woman cloathed in Scarlet,</hi> a bloody colour. It was at firſt planted, and afterwards watered with blood. The ten per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Roman Emperours ſlew ſo many Chriſtians, as that we are told 5000 Martyrs may be aſſigned to every day in the year except one. And the learned Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> tells us, that the Perſecution of the Beaſt, or of the Papacy, was as great as that of the Roman Heathen Emperours. And here, <hi>Qualis Rex, talis Grex,</hi> as were their Rulers and Governours, ſuch, ſo cruel and bloody were the common People; witneſs the great delight the Roman Citizens took, in beholding the Sword-ſights, where ſometimes out of an opinion, that it was good againſt the Falling-ſickneſs, they ſucked the reak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blood out of the freſh wounds (as well as bathed their hands in the blood) of the ſlain.<note place="margin">D. H. <hi>from</hi> Pl.</note> They were void of natural affection; they had no Bowels for them that came out of their own Bowels; for they ſometimes expoſed, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times murthered their own Children, if Females, if deform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or if the Parents were poor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea ſometimes they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered their own Children in Sacrifice to their Idol-Gods, as alſo did the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> the <hi>Gaules,</hi> and ſome of the ancient <hi>Britains;</hi> Thus they became more brutiſh, more ſavage than the very wild Beaſts; for which of theſe doth not love, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, nouriſh, and cheriſh their Young, the fruit of their own Bodies?</p>
               <p>And well it were if only Heathens were guilty of ſuch cruelty, and liable to ſuch reproof. How many Chriſtian Parents are there, of whom it may be ſaid, as the Emperour ſaid of <hi>Herod,</hi> that it was better to be his Swine, than his Son? Better to have been their Beaſts, than their Children? I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not excuſe King <hi>Philip</hi> the II. of <hi>Spain,</hi> that delivered up, or at leaſt permitted his own Son Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> the Heir of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48506:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Crown to be put to death in the Inquiſition. Beloved, theſe things ought not ſo to be; If you muſt be kind to you Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, then much more to your own Children, you muſt not hide your eyes from your own fleſh; you muſt not make their lives bitter to them, bitter as death, by reaſon of your harſhneſs and ſeverity.</p>
               <p>Again, hence be convinced of your duty, and perſwaded to it. Ye that are Maſters of Servants, be kind not cruel to them. If we muſt not be cruel to the Beaſts, much leſs to our Brother, fleſh of our fleſh, and bone of our bone. Your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, if Chriſtians eſpecially, are your Brethren, your Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ſervants; you and they have one and the ſame Maſter in Heaven.</p>
               <p>To draw towards a Concluſion, Let's not be cruel to our own ſelves, our own Souls or Bodies. Let not any Man lay violent hands upon himſelf. Let not any Man that is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian be <hi>felo de ſe.</hi> Let not ſuicide or ſelf-murther be once named among Chriſtians. We are Souldiers, have our place and ſtation ſet us, and muſt not ſtir off the Guard till our General, the Lord of Hoſts, call us off again. We muſt not break Priſon to ſet our Souls at liberty, but ſtay till death come with power and authority from the Lord of liberty, life, and death to let them out. Who ever hated his own fleſh?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Let's be kindly affected one towards another, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man to his Brother and his Neighbour; be not Men-eaters in the worſt ſenſe; do not bite and devour one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; do not eat one another as one eateth Bread. If we muſt not rent Chriſt's ſeamles Coat, ſurely we muſt not tear and devour Chriſt's living Body. Let not our Swords any more eat one anothers fleſh, or drink one anothers blood any more. The Sword hath a mouth, the edge of the Sword in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew ſignifies the mouth of the Sword. If we do thus eat up one another, or cruelly ſhed one anothers blood any more, know, that <hi>the voice of thy Brothers blood will cry to Heaven</hi> for vengeance, as the blood of <hi>Abel</hi> did againſt <hi>Cain,</hi> &amp; the Souls under the Altar in the <hi>Revelations, How long Lord, Holy and True, will it be, before thou avenge our blood upon them that have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly ſhed it!</hi> or rather, ſpilt our blood, like water upon the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:48506:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Earth! Doth God take care for Oxen or other Beaſts, in this Text? Doubtleſs as unto us, ſo for our ſakes chiefly and ultimately was this written: <hi>A good Man is merciful to his Beaſt, but the mercies of the wicked are cruel:</hi> As if the Wiſe-man had ſaid, A juſt or good Man is merciful to the Beaſts; but a wicked Man is cruel and merciles to Mankind. And take this along with you; That, to uſe to ſhew mercy to our Beaſts, is a way and means to make us merciful to our Brother and Neighbour. <hi>Si quis Conſcientiâ Divini mandati ad cruentandum jumentum, tardior ſuerit; eum certè ad Hominem violandum, multo magis averſum &amp; alienum habebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> So <hi>Chriſoſt. in Loc.</hi> 'Tis thought that God moſt merciful forbad to eat Blood after the Flood, to prevent the violence that did overflow the earth before the Deluge came; for thoſe two go together, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. <hi>He that ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Man's blood, by Man ſhall his blood be ſhed;</hi> And, <hi>Ye ſhall not eat the blood of the Beaſt, becauſe,</hi> or for, <hi>the life is in the blood</hi> Thoſe who are uſed to ſhed blood though the blood of Beaſts, and though for neceſſity and publick good, as Butchers amongſt us, are forbidden by the Law (or may be excepted againſt) if impannel'd upon a Jury of life and death; becauſe their calling, as is conceived, doth harden their hearts, or at leaſt make them leſs inclined to mercy and pity than other Men. Even doubtleſs the cruel Spectacles at <hi>Rome</hi> did render the People leſs mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful. 'Tis very probable that the cuſtom there, of caſting Malefactours to the Lyons and other wild Beaſts, to be devoured by them; and the cuſtom of ſetting Beaſts to ſight with, and kill one another in the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, might diſpoſe them the more eaſily to delight in the Sword-ſights, wherein Men ſlaughtered one another, to the great content, ſatisfaction and joy of the Beholders, and ſo though their hands were not, yet, they had their eyes in blood, and as <hi>he that lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ks on a Woman to luſt after her, hath committed Adultery with her already in his heart;</hi> ſo he that looked on theſe bloody Spectacles with a deſire that one ſhould kill the other, and delighted therein when done, committed Murther againſt his Brother in his heart: And as 'tis ſaid of ſome <hi>that they had eyes full of Adultery,</hi> ſo we may ſay of the Spectatours of theſe bloody Fights, that they had eyes full of Murther; Their eyes were blood ſhot in the worſt ſenſe, their eyes were full of blood.</p>
               <p>Beloved, let it not be ſo amongſt you; you are Chriſtians, Children of the Father of Mercies; your Boſoms are the neſt of the Heavenly Dove; &amp; you expect to follow the Lamb where ever he goes. You who before your call &amp; converſion were as Lyons, Tygres, Wolves, Bears, as cruel as ſuch one to another, Put on as the Elect of God, bowels of mercy, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, gentleneſs; you who formerly lived in malice &amp; envy, hateful &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one another; now that the kindneſs and love of God our Saviour towards man hath appeared; ſee that all bitterneſs, wrath, clamour and evil ſpeaking be put away from you, with all malice; &amp; be ye kind one to another, tender hearted like the good <hi>Samaritan,</hi> not only kind to your Neighbours, but even to Strangers, and like to the righteous Man in the Text, whoſe character is, that <hi>he is merciful to,</hi> or regardeth, <hi>the life of his Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48506:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
